<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Navigation rectified: or, the common chart proved to be the only true chart. By Peter Blackborow</title>
            <author>Blackborow, Peter.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 168 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 90 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76785</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3062</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202422</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897729</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897729</idno>
            <idno type="VID">135346</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76785)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 135346)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2525:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Navigation rectified: or, the common chart proved to be the only true chart. By Peter Blackborow</title>
                  <author>Blackborow, Peter.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 157, [1] p., plates   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by John Playford, and are to be sold by Joseph Hindmarsh, bookseller to His Royal Highness, at the Black Bull in Cornhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Navigation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:135346:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135346:1"/>
            <p>NAVIGATION RECTIFIED: OR, THE <hi>COMMON CHART</hi> Proved to be the only TRUE CHART. By <hi>Peter Blackborow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>John Playford,</hi> and are to be Sold by <hi>Joſeph Hindmarſh,</hi> Bookſeller to His Royal Highneſs, at the <hi>Black Bull</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:135346:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135346:2"/>
            <p>TO ALL MEN <hi>That are Studious in</hi> NAVIGATION THIS TREATISE (Upon the Three Principal Kinds of Sayling, ſo called, wherein there is ſo great diſproportion, that the Queſtion may be asked, what is Truth in <hi>Navigation?</hi> Wherein is proved by Obſervation and Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, that there is but one Truth in <hi>Navigation,</hi> and that is the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Chart which is ſo much reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by all Writers, ſo that all other Poſitions in <hi>Navigation</hi> muſt be rejected; if you will follow that which is Truth)</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Is DEDICATED By</hi> Peter Blackborow.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:135346:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135346:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>NAVIGATION</hi> muſt depend upon the Magnetick Compaſs, and the Latitude of places by Obſervation, otherwiſe you cannot ſhape your Courſe to any place in the World, by the Rumb, and the Right Lines of the Magnetick Compaſs, and whereas you have three principal kinds of Sailing ſo called: The Common Chart, <hi>Mercator,</hi> and the Arch of a Great Circle, wherein it will appear there is ſo great diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion between the one and the other, that the Queſtion may be asked, which of the three is Truth? There is but
<pb facs="tcp:135346:4"/> one Truth in <hi>Navigation,</hi> and tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may be always Demonſtrated to be ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo that although the Earth and Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are Spherical, I ſhall prove by Obſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vation, and Demonſtration, that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Magnetick Compaſs, as it is Horizon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tal, meaſures the Superficies of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Earth and Sea by Right Lines, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> if the Superficies of the Globe wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a Plain to the Horizon: Therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhall firſt reſolve the Queſtion by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Rumb and the Right Lines of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Magnetick Compaſs, in a Right line<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Triangle, which is in proportion to the Common Chart.</p>
            <p>Then I ſhall ſhew you how the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridians and Parallels of places in the Common Chart, are transferred into the Meridians and Parallels of the Globe.</p>
            <p>Then I ſhall reſolve the ſame Queſtion by <hi>Mercator</hi> as is given
<pb facs="tcp:135346:4"/> in the Common Chart, wherein I ſhall ſhew you how great the disproportion is between the Meridians of <hi>Mercator</hi> and the Meridians of the Common Chart: And laſt of all, I ſhall ſhew you wherein the disproportion appears to be a groſs errour in <hi>Mercator,</hi> in miſtaking the Meridians of the Magnetick Compaſs.</p>
            <p>Then I ſhall reſolve the ſame Queſtion by the Arch of a Great Circle, wherein it will appear the Arch of a Great Circle gives a nearer diſtance than is contained in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallels of Latitude, which alters the Angles of Poſition in the Arch of a Great Circle from the Angles of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition by the Magnetick Compaſs, that you cannot give the Queſtion from the Practical part of the Sea, but you muſt alter the Meridians and Paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lels
<pb facs="tcp:135346:5"/> of places upon the Globe, ſo th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Work of <hi>Navigation</hi> cannot b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> performed by the Arch of a Grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Circle, in proportion to the Rum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and the Right-lines of the Magnetic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Compaſs.</p>
            <p>In the Concluſion it will appear by Obſervation and Demonſtration, that the Common Chart that hath been ſo much rejected by all Writers, is the only Truth in <hi>Navigation.</hi> All which I would deſire you to accept with the ſame Candour and Integrity, as it is offered by him, who is,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A Lover of the MATHEMATICS, <hi>Peter Blackborow.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:135346:5"/>
            <head>NAVIGATION RECTIFIED.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL the known part of the World hath been diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by the Magnetick Compaſs, and the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of Places by Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, which doth produce the difference of Longtitude, and the diſtance of places in a Right-lined Triangle: Therefore the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netick Compaſs is of that ſingular uſe in <hi>Navigation,</hi> that all Queſtions muſt be reſolved in proportion to the Rumb and the Right-lines of the Magnetick Compaſs, otherwiſe you have no
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:135346:6"/> Geometrical Demonſtration in <hi>Navi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation:</hi> So that all the known parts of the World are laid down in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Chart in proportion to the Rumb and the Right Lines of the Magnetick Compaſs.</p>
            <p>Then obſerve, the Superficies of the Earth and Sea being Spherical, the Lines of the Globe muſt be Oblique, which differ from the Rumb and the Right-lines of the Magnetick Compaſs and of the Common Chart, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is an abſolute neceſſity to find ſuch proportions from the Globe, as may be in proportion to the Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians and Parallels of the Common Chart; otherwiſe the Meridians and Parallels of places in the Common Chart, cannot be transferred into the Globe according to the Meridians and Parallels of the Globe: So that all the known part of the World is laid down in the Meridians and Parallels of the Globe from the Meridians and Parallels of the Common Chart, for the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Longitude in the Common Chart between places differing in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:135346:6"/> Longitude and Latitude, is proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal to the difference of Meridians in the middle Parallel between ſuch pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces differing in Longitude and Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude upon the Globe: And where places in the Common Chart differ in Longitude, being in one and the ſame Parallel, their diſtance is the ſame in the Globe as it is in the Common Chart, for the diſtance is transferred from the Common Chart, to the Globe, notwithſtanding it will appear by the following demonſtrations, that you cannot perform the Work of <hi>Naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> by the Oblique-lines of the Globe, in regard the Oblique-lines of the Globe differ from the Rumb, and the Right-lines of the Magnetick Compaſs, ſo that the Angles of Poſition in all Oblique-angles differ from the Angles of Poſition by the Magnetick Compaſs. Therefore I ſhall take this method: Firſt, I ſhall reſolve the Queſtion by the Common Chart: Then I ſhall ſhew you how the Meridians and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallels of places in the Common Chart are transferred into the Meridians and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:135346:7"/> Parallels of the Globe, and in the next place I ſhall reſolve the ſame Queſtion by <hi>Mercator:</hi> And laſt of all I ſhall reſolve the ſame Queſtion by the Arch of a Great Circle; all which are the three principal kinds of Sayling ſo called by all Writers; from whence I ſhall prove the Common Chart, that hath been ſo much rejected by all Writers to be the only Truth in <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation,</hi> for you muſt Sail by the Rumb and the Right-lines of the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netick Compaſs, or the Magnetick Compaſs is of little uſe in <hi>Naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> I ſhall reſolve the Queſtion by the Common Chart.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>geometrical diagram</figDesc>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Pag:</hi> 5.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>The Angle following being a Right-lined Triangle, and is in the like pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Common Chart, ſo is L, the Meridian and Parallel of the <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard,</hi> and B is the Meridian and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel of <hi>Bermudas:</hi> Then is L, A, the difference of Latitude, 1055 Miles, and C L D, is the Rumb or Angle of Poſition between the Meridian and Parallel of the <hi>Lyzard</hi> and the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian and Parallel of <hi>Bermudas</hi> 71 <hi>d.</hi> 10 <hi>m.</hi> and A B is the difference of Longitude, and L B is the diſtance between the Meridian and Parallel of the <hi>Lyzard</hi> and the Meridian and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel of <hi>Bermudas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the following demonſtration, an Inch divided into ten equal parts is to be accounted for 1000 Miles, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the diſtance is great, and ſo many equal parts cannot be diſcerned in ſo ſmall a ſpace.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:135346:9"/>
               <p>By the Geometrical meaſure, the difference of Longitude is A B, 3093 Miles, and the diſtance is L B, 3268 Miles, all which is in like proportion to the Common Chart.</p>
               <p>To find the difference of Longitude, the proportions Arithmetical, <hi>As the Radius</hi> 90 d. A B N, 1000000; <hi>is to the Logarithm of the difference of Latitude</hi> 1055 <hi>Miles,</hi> L A, 302325: <hi>ſo is the Tangent of the Rumb</hi> 71 d. 10 m. A, L, B, 1046714. <hi>to the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garithm of the difference of Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude</hi> 349039, A B, 3093 Miles. Add the Logarithm of the difference of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, to the Tangent of the Rumb, and Subtract the Radius, and you have the Logarithm of the difference of Longitude 349039, A B, 3093 Miles; ſo that the difference of Latitude and the Rumb by the Magnetick Compaſs, is in proportion in a Right-lined Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angle to the difference of Longitude in the Common Chart.</p>
               <p>To find the diſtance, the propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions Arithmetical: <hi>As the Co-ſine of the Rumb</hi> 71d. 10 m. A, B, L, 950895;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:135346:9"/> 
                  <hi>Is to the Logarithm of the difference of Latitude</hi> 1055 m. L A, 302325: <hi>So is the Radius</hi> 90 d. L, A, B, 1000000; <hi>to the Logarithm of the diſtance</hi> 351430, L B, 3268 Miles. Add the Logarithm of the difference of Latitude to the Radius, and Subtract the Co-ſine of the Rumb, and you have the Logar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ithm of the diſtance 351430, L, B, 3268 Miles; ſo that the difference of Latitude and the Rumb by the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netick Compaſs, is in proportion in a Right-lined Triangle, to the diſtance in the Common Chart.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> I ſhall give the Rumb 71 <hi>d.</hi> 10 <hi>m.</hi> A L B; and the difference of Longitude 3093 <hi>m.</hi> A B; and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the difference of Latitude L A, and the diſtance L B.</p>
               <p>I have already given you the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of the Geometrical part of all Queſtions, that are to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved between the Meridian and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel of the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> and the Meridian and Parallel of <hi>Bermudas,</hi> for as it ſtands in the foregoing demonſtration
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:135346:10"/> it is in the like proportion in the Com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon Chart, therefore I ſhall procee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to the Arithmetical proportion.</p>
               <p>To find the difference of Latitude the proportions Arithmetical; <hi>As the Tangent of the Rumb</hi> 71 <hi>d.</hi> 10 <hi>m.</hi> A L B, 1046714; <hi>Is to the Logarithm of the difference of Longitude</hi> 3093 m. A B, 349037: <hi>So is the Radius</hi> 90 d. A B N, 13000000; <hi>To the Logarithm of the difference of Latitude</hi> 302323, L A, 1055 <hi>m</hi> Add the Logarithm of the difference of Longitude to the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius, and Subtract the Tangent of the Rumb, and you have the Logarithm of the difference of Latitude 302323, LA, 1055: So that the Rumb, by the Magnetick Compaſs, and the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Longitude is in proportion in a Right-lined Triangle, to the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of Latitude in the Common Chart.</p>
               <p>To find the diſtance, the proportions Arithmetical: <hi>As the Sine of the Rumb</hi> 71 d. 10 m. A L B, 997610; <hi>Is to the Logarithm of the difference of Longitude</hi> 3093, L A, 349037: <hi>So is the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:135346:10"/> 90 d. L A B, 1000000; <hi>to the Logarithm of the diſtance</hi> 351427, L B; 3268 m. Add the Logarithm of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he difference of Longitude to the Radius, and Subtract the Sine of the Rumb, and you have the Logarithm of the diſtance 351427, L B; 3268 Miles: So that the difference of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude, and the Rumb by the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netick Compaſs, is in proportion in a Right-lined Triangle, to the diſtance in the Common Chart.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Third<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y,</hi> I ſhall give you the Rumb A L B, 71 <hi>d.</hi> 10 <hi>m.</hi> and the diſtance L B, 3268 <hi>m.</hi> and demand the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Longitude A B, and the difference of Latitude L A.</p>
               <p>To find the difference of Longitude, the proportions Arithmetical: <hi>As the Radius</hi> 90 d. L A B, 1000000; <hi>is to the Logarithm of the diſtance,</hi> 3268 m. L B, 351428: <hi>So is the Sine of the Rumb</hi> 71 d. 10 m. A L B, 997610; <hi>to the Logarithm of the difference of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude</hi> 349038, A B, 3093 m. Add the Logarithm of the diſtance to the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:135346:11"/> Sine of the Rumb, and Subtract the Radius, and you have the Logarithm of the difference of Longitude, 349038, A B, 3093 <hi>m.</hi> ſo that the Rumb and the diſtance by the Magne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Compaſs, is in proportion in a Right-lined Triangle, to the difference of Longitude in the Common Chart.</p>
               <p>To find the difference of Latitude, the proportions Arithmetical: <hi>As the Radius</hi> 90 d. L A B, 1000000, <hi>is to the Logarithm of the Diſtance</hi> 3268 m. L B, 351428: <hi>So is the Co-ſine of the Rumb</hi> 71 d. 10 m. A B L, 950896, <hi>to the Logarithm of the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Latitude,</hi> 302323, L A, 1055 <hi>m.</hi> Add the Longarithm of the diſtance to the Co-ſine of the Rumb, and Subtract the Radius, and you have the Logarithm of the difference of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude 302323, L A, 1055 <hi>m.</hi> So that the Rumb, and the diſtance by the Magnetick Compaſs, is in proportion to the difference of Latitude in the Common Chart.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> I ſhall give the difference
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:135346:11"/> of Latitude L A, 1055 <hi>m.</hi> and the difference of Longitude A B, 3093 <hi>m.</hi> and demand the Rumb by the Magnetick Compaſs A L B.</p>
               <p>To find the Rumb by the Magnetick Compaſs, the proportions Arithme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical: <hi>As the Logarithm of the difference of Latitude</hi> 1055 m. L A, 302325, <hi>is to the Radius</hi> 90 d. A B N, 1000000; <hi>ſo is the Logarithm of the difference of Longitude</hi> 3093 <hi>m.</hi> A B, 349037; <hi>to the Tangent of the Rumb</hi> 1046712; A L B, 71 d. 10 m. Add the Radius to the Logarithm of the difference of Longitude, and Subtract the Loga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rithm of the difference of Latitude, and you have the Tangent of the Rumb, 1046712; A L B, 71 <hi>d.</hi> 10 <hi>m.</hi> So that the difference of Latitude, and the difference of Longitude, is in proportion to the Rumb, by the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netick Compſs, in the Common Chart.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> I ſhall give the difference of Latitude L A, 1055 <hi>m.</hi> and the diſtance L B, 3268 Miles, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:135346:12"/> demand the Rumb by the Magnetic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Compaſs.</p>
               <p>To find the Rumb by the Magnetic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Compaſs, the proportions Arithmeti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cal: <hi>As the Logarithm of the diſtance</hi> 326<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> m. L B, 351428, <hi>is to the Radius</hi> 90 d<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> L A B, 1000000; <hi>ſo is the Logarithm of the difference of Latitude</hi> 1055 m<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> L A, 302325; <hi>to the Co-ſine of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Rumb</hi> 950897, A B L, 18 d. 50 m <hi>whoſe Complement is</hi> 71 d. 10 <hi>m.</hi> A L B<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> So that the difference of Latitude an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diſtance of places, is in proportion t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Rumb, by the Magnetick Compaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the Common Chart. Add the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garithm of the difference of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude to the Radius, and Subtrac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Logarithm of the diſtance, and you have the Coſine of the Rumb 950897, A B L, 18 <hi>d.</hi> 50 <hi>m.</hi> whoſe complement is 71 <hi>d.</hi> 10 <hi>m.</hi> A L B, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixthly,</hi> I ſhall give the difference of Longitude 3093 <hi>m.</hi> A B; and the diſtance 3268 <hi>m.</hi> L B. and demand the Rumb by the Magnetick Compaſs.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:135346:12"/>
               <p>To find the Rumb by the Magnetick Compaſs, the proportions Arithme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical: <hi>As the Logarithm of the diſtance</hi> 3268 m. L B, 351428; <hi>is to the Radius</hi> 90 d. L A B, 1000000: <hi>So is the Logarithm of the difference of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude</hi> 3093 m. A B, 349037; <hi>to the Sine of the Rumb</hi> 997609, A L B, 71 d. 10 m. Add the Radius to the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garithm of the difference of Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and Subtract the Logarithm of the diſtance, and you have the Sine of the Rumb 997609, A L B, 71 <hi>d.</hi> 10 <hi>m.</hi> So that the difference of Longitude, and the diſtance is in proportion to the Rumb in the Common Chart.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seventhly,</hi> I ſhall give the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Longitude 3093 <hi>m.</hi> A B, and the diſtance 3268 <hi>m.</hi> L B, and demand the difference of Latitude L A.</p>
               <p>To find the difference of Latitude, the proportions Arithmetical: Add the difference of Longitude 3093 m. to the diſtance 3268 m. and you have 6361 Mil. for the ſum of the ſides; then Subtract the difference of Longitude
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:135346:13"/> from the diſtance, and you hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 175 Miles for the difference of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſides; ſo take the Logarithm of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſum of the ſides A B, L B, 6361 Mile<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 380352; and the Logarithm of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> difference of the ſides 175 Miles 224303: Add them together, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you have 604655, the half is 302327<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which is the Logarithm of the diffe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rence of Latitude 1055 <hi>m.</hi> L A. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that the difference of Longitude, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the diſtance is in proportion in a Right lined Triangle, in the Common Chart<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eightly,</hi> I ſhall give the differenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Latitude L A, 1055 <hi>m.</hi> and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diſtance L B, 3268 <hi>m.</hi> and demand th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> difference of Longitude.</p>
               <p>To find the difference of Longitude the proportions Arithmetical; Ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the difference of Latitude 1055 <hi>m.</hi> to the diſtance 3268 <hi>m.</hi> and you have 4323 Miles for the ſum of the ſides then Subtract the difference of Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude from the diſtance, and you have 2213 Miles for the difference of the ſides: So take the Logarithm of the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:135346:13"/> ſum of the ſides 4323 Miles, L A, L B, 363578; and the Logarithm of the difference of the ſides, 2213, 334498: Add them together, and you have 698076, the half is 349038, which is the Logarithm of the difference of Longitude 3093 Miles, A B: So that the difference of Latitude, and the diſtance is in proportion in a Right-lined Triangle, in the Common Chart.</p>
               <p>I have proved by the foregoing Queſtions, that the Rumb and the Right-lines of the Magnetick Compaſs, agree with the Rumb and the Right-lines of the Common Chart, from hence may ariſe an objection, how the Right-lines of the Magnetick Compaſs can meaſure the Superficies of the Globe, which is ſpherical? To anſwer this objection, I will grant you to be in any Meridian and Parallel of the World, wherein you muſt ſee 180 <hi>d.</hi> of Heaven, for it is 90 <hi>d.</hi> from your Zenith every way to the Horizon, then the Circulation of the Horizon muſt
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:135346:14"/> contain 360 <hi>d.</hi> To this I compare t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Magnetick Compaſs, which contai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 360 <hi>d.</hi> and is Horizontal to the H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rizon always, in all Meridians an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Parallels of the World; So that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> North and South, and the Eaſt an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Weſt Points of the Magnetick Com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>paſs, point to the Celeſtial Poles o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> North and South, and to the Celeſtia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Poles of Eaſt and Weſt, in all Me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ridians and Parallels of the Earth and Sea, without giving any diffe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rence of obſervation for the Semi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>Diameter of the Earth and Sea; the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Meridians of the Magnetick Compaſs, muſt run parallel to the Poles of Eaſt and Weſt, as the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallels of Latitude run parallel to the Poles of North and South; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Magnetick Compaſs being of Right-lines, meaſures the Superficies of the Globe by Right-lines, as if the Superficies of the Globe was always a Plain to the Horizon; ſo that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever poſition doth diſagree with the Rumb and the Right-lines of the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netick Compaſs muſt be a falſe poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:135346:14"/> in Navigation, for the work of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>avigation muſt be performed by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>agnetick Compaſs, and the Latitude <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> places by obſervation, by which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eans all the known parts of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orld have been diſcovered, and laid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>own in a Plain in the Common Chart: Therefore I ſhall ſhew you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow the difference of Latitude and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ifference of Longitude, and the diſtance of places in the Common Chart is transferr'd, in proportion to the difference of Latitude, and the diſtance of places upon the Globe; wherein I ſhall prove by demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that the Meridian of the Magne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Compaſs doth differ from the Meridians of the Globe, as they are drawn.</p>
               <p>To prove how the difference of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, and the diſtance of places, and the difference of Longitude in the Common Chart, is transferred from the Common Chart, to be in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion by Demonſtration to the difference of Latitude, and the diſtance of places upon the Globe:</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:135346:15"/>
               <p>In the foregoing Queſtion, by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Common Chart, the <hi>Lizard</hi> is in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Latitude of 50 <hi>d.</hi> 00 <hi>m.</hi> the <hi>Bermudu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> is in the Latitude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> difference of Latitude is 1055 <hi>m</hi> or 17 <hi>d.</hi> 35 <hi>m.</hi> and the difference o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Longitude is 3093 <hi>m.</hi> or 51 <hi>d.</hi> 33 <hi>m.</hi> and the diſtance is 3268 <hi>m.</hi> or 54 <hi>d.</hi> 28 <hi>m.</hi> before I proceed to the demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration upon the Globe, you may obſerve the difference of Longitude in all Right-lined Triangles, is in proportion to the difference of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude in the middle parallel of the Globe, between ſuch place diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in Longitude and Latitude, in all Meridians and parallels of the World.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>geometrical diagram</figDesc>
                  <head>Pag: 19</head>
               </figure>
               <p>TO prove how the difference of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, and the diſtance of places, and the difference of Longitude in the Common Chart is transferr'd by demonſtration, to be in proportion to the difference of Latitude, and the diſtance of places upon the Globe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>EXAMPLE.</label> The <hi>Lyzard</hi> is in the Latitude of 50 <hi>d.</hi> 00 <hi>m.</hi> L. <hi>Bermudus</hi> is in the Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> B, their difference of Latitude is A L, 17 <hi>d.</hi> 35 <hi>m.</hi> the half thereof is 08 <hi>d.</hi> 47 <hi>m.</hi> 30 <hi>ſec.</hi> which being added to D A, 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> the Latitude of <hi>Bermudus,</hi> you have D E, 41 <hi>d.</hi> 12 <hi>m.</hi> 30 <hi>ſec.</hi> the Latitude of the middle parallel between the <hi>Lizard</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:135346:17"/> and <hi>Bermudus,</hi> then reduce the di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rence of Longitude found by the fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> going Right-lined Triangle, betwe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Meridian and parallel of the <hi>Lyza<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and the Meridian and parallel of <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mudus,</hi> 3093 <hi>m.</hi> into Degrees of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Aequinoctial, by dividing 3093 by 60 <hi>m.</hi> and you have 51 <hi>d.</hi> 33 which diſtance being taken by you Compaſs, from the Aequinoctial pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the Globe, and meaſuring th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diſtance in the middle parallel E <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 41 <hi>d.</hi> 12 <hi>m.</hi> 30 <hi>ſec.</hi> you will find tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diſtance 51 <hi>d.</hi> 33 <hi>m.</hi> to reach from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Meridian of the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> to the Mer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dian of the <hi>Bermudus,</hi> in the paralle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of 41 <hi>d.</hi> 12 <hi>m.</hi> 30 <hi>ſec.</hi> which is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſame diſtance in the Common Chart ſo that the <hi>Lyzard</hi> muſt be laid down upon the Globe, in the Meridian o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the middle parallel D E P, and in the Latitude of 50 <hi>d.</hi> 00 <hi>m.</hi> at L, and <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mudus</hi> muſt be laid down upon the Globe in the Meridian of the middle parallel C E P, and in the Latitude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> at B.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:135346:17"/>
               <p>In the next place, I ſhall ſhew you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w to find the diſtance by the Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etrical part of the Globe, to be in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oportion to the diſtance found by a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ght-lined Triangle between the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dian and parallel of the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd the Meridian and parallel of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ermudus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>EXAMPLE.</label> Reduce the diſtance found by a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight-lined Triangle 3268 <hi>m.</hi> by 60 <hi>m.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto degrees of the Aequinoctial, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ividing 3268 <hi>m.</hi> by 60 <hi>m.</hi> and you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ave 54 <hi>d.</hi> 28 <hi>m.</hi> which diſtance being taken by your Compaſs, from the Aequinoctial part of the Globe, that diſtance will reach from the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian and parallel of the <hi>Lyzard</hi> L, to the Meridian and parallel of <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mudus</hi> B, ſo that the diſtance between the Meridian and parallel of the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> and the Meridian and parallel of <hi>Bermudus,</hi> is the ſame in the Globe as it is in a Right-lined Triangle.</p>
               <p>Having proved how the difference of Latitude, and the diſtance of places,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:135346:18"/> and the difference of Longitude in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Common Chart, is transferred from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Common Chart, to be in propotio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by demonſtration to the difference o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Latitude, and the difference of Longi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tude in the middle parallel, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diſtance of places on the Globe:</p>
               <p>In the next place, you may obſerv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the difference of Longitude in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Globe, between the Meridians of the middle parallel 41 <hi>d.</hi> 12. <hi>m.</hi> 30 <hi>ſec</hi> E F, is 3093 <hi>m.</hi> or 51 <hi>d.</hi> 33 <hi>m.</hi> And the difference of Longitude in the Aequinoctial part of the Globe, between thoſe Meridians D C is 4200 <hi>m.</hi> or 70 <hi>d.</hi> 00 <hi>m.</hi> and the difference of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude between thoſe Meridians, in the parallel of <hi>Bermudus,</hi> A B, is 3545 <hi>m.</hi> or 59 <hi>d.</hi> 05 <hi>m.</hi> and the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Longitude, between thoſe Meridians in the parallel of the <hi>Lyzard</hi> L G is 2700 Miles, or 45 <hi>d.</hi> 00 <hi>m.</hi> all which diſtances may be meaſured upon the Globe; from whence you may make this obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, that the difference of Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude in the Globe, between the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:135346:18"/> and Parallel of <hi>Bermudus</hi> B, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd the Meridian of the <hi>Lyzard</hi> A B, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>545 <hi>m.</hi> 59 <hi>d.</hi> 05 <hi>m.</hi> and the diſtance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y the Common Chart, between the Meridian and Parallel of the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd the Meridian and parallel of <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mudus,</hi> is 3268 <hi>m.</hi> or 54 <hi>d.</hi> 28 <hi>m.</hi> So that the difference of Longitude in the Globe, between the Meridian and parallel of <hi>Bermudus,</hi> and the Meridian of the <hi>Lyzard</hi> is 277 <hi>m.</hi> or 04 <hi>d.</hi> 37 <hi>m.</hi> more than the diſtance between the Meridian and parallel of the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> and the Meridian and Parallel of <hi>Bermudus,</hi> which is out of all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion to the Rumb, and the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Longitude and the diſtance of places in a Right-lined Triangle; for the difference of Longitude in Navigation, by the Magnetick Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs cannot be greater than the diſtance: So that the work of Navi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation cannot be performed by the Globe, before you have found ſuch proportions upon the Globe, which are in proportion to the Rumb, and the Right-lines of the Magnetick
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:135346:19"/> Compaſs, as the Queſtion hath b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> transferr'd to the Globe from Common Chart.</p>
               <p>In the next place I ſhall give <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Arithmetical proportions of Globe, which are in proportion the Geometrical part.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Lyzard</hi> is in the Latitude 50 <hi>d.</hi> 00 <hi>m.</hi> L, <hi>Bermudus</hi> is in Latitude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> B, their di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rence of Longitude in the Aequinoct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> part of the Globe is 70 <hi>d.</hi> 00 <hi>m</hi> D I demand the difference of Longitu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the middle parallel E F.</p>
               <p>To find the Logarithm of the diff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rence of Longitude, between the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ridian and Parallel of the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Meridian of <hi>Bermudus</hi> L G, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> proportion Arithmetical: <hi>As the R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dius</hi> 90 d. P D, 1000000, <hi>is to the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>garithm of the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fference of Longitu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in the Aequinoctial,</hi> 70 d. 00 m. 4200 m. D C, 362324; <hi>ſo is the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſine of the Latitude of the</hi> Lyzard 40 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 00 <hi>m.</hi> P L, 980806, <hi>to the Logarithm of</hi> L G, 343130. Add the Logarithm of the difference of Longitude in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:135346:19"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Aequinoctial to the Co-ſine of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atitude, and Subtract the Radius, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou have the Logarithm of the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nce of Longitude between the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dian and parallel of the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Meridiad of <hi>Bermudus,</hi> L G, 43130, or 2700 <hi>m.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To find the Logarithm of the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ence of Longitude between the Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ian and parallel of <hi>Bermudus,</hi> and the Meridian of the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> B A, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ortions Arithmetical: <hi>As the Radius</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0 d. 00 m. P D, 1000000; <hi>is to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ogarithm of the difference of Longitude <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n the Aequinoctial,</hi> 70 d. 00 m. <hi>or</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>200 m. D C, 362324: <hi>So is the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ine of the Latitude of</hi> Bermudus 57 d. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5 m. A P, 992643; <hi>to the Logarithm of</hi> A B, 354967: Add the Logarithm of the difference of Longitude in the Aequinoctial, to the Co-ſine of the Latitude, and Subtract the Radius, and you have the Logarithm of the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Longitude, between the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian and parallel of <hi>Bermudus,</hi> and the Meridian of the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> A B, 354967, or 3545 <hi>m.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:135346:20"/>
               <p>Then add the Logarithm of 34<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> found in proportion, to 70 <hi>d.</hi> 00 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Longitude, in the parallel of 00 <hi>m.</hi> to the Logarithm of 354 found in proportion to 70 <hi>d.</hi> 00 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Longitude, in the parallel of 25 <hi>m.</hi> and you have 698097, the in 3490481/2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which is the Logari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of the difference of Longitude in middle parallel, between the Meri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and parallel of the <hi>Lyzard</hi> and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ridian and parallel of <hi>Bermudus,</hi> 3093 <hi>m.</hi> or 51 <hi>d.</hi> 33 <hi>m.</hi> So that the portions Arithmetical do agree w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the proportions Geometrical, wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you have the middle parallel 3093 the proper difference of Longitude, which the difference of Latitude, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the diſtance upon the Globe, is in li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> proportion in the common Chart.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſt of all,</hi> I ſhall give the Queſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> from the difference of Longitu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in a Right-lined Triangle, and the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of the <hi>Lyzard</hi> and <hi>Bermudu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and demand the difference of Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude in the Aequinoctial part of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Globe.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:135346:20"/>
               <p>
                  <label>EXAMPLE.</label> Sail from the <hi>Lyzard</hi> in the Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of 50 <hi>d.</hi> 00 <hi>m.</hi> L, between the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith and the Weſt, in the Latitude 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> B, I find my difference Longitude in a Right-lined Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gle, 3093 <hi>m.</hi> I demand the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ce of Longitude in the Aequinoctial <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t of the Globe, between the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ian of the <hi>Lyzard</hi> and the Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>n of <hi>Bermudus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To find the difference of Longitude the Aequinoctial, the proportions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ithmetical: <hi>As the Co-ſine of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>titude of the</hi> Lyzard, 40 d. 00 m. L, 980806; <hi>is to the Logarithm of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e difference of Longitude in the middle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rallel of the Globe,</hi> 3093 m E F, 49037: <hi>So is the Radius</hi> 90 d. 00 m. D, 1000000; <hi>to the Logarithm of</hi> 68231: Add the Logarithm of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ifference of Longitude in the middle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arallel to the Radius, and Subtract <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Co-ſine of the Latitude, and you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ave the Logarithm of 368231,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:135346:21"/> which muſt be added to the n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> proportion.</p>
               <p>Then, <hi>As</hi> the Co-ſine of the Latitu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>Bermudus,</hi> 57 <hi>d.</hi> 35 <hi>m.</hi> P A, 99264 <hi>is to</hi> the Logarithm of the differe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of Longitude in the parallel of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Globe, 3093 <hi>m.</hi> E F, 349037: <hi>So</hi> the Radius 90 <hi>d.</hi> oo <hi>m.</hi> P D, 100000<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>to</hi> the Logarithm of 356394: A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Logarithm of the difference Longitude in the middle parallel, the Radius, and Subtract the Co-ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of the Latitude, and you have t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Logarithm of 356394:</p>
               <p>Then add the Logarithm of 36823 (found in proportion to 3093 <hi>m.</hi> Longitude in the parallel of 50<hi>d.</hi> 00<hi>m</hi> to the Logarithm of 356394, (found <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> proportion to 3093 <hi>m.</hi> of Longitude, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the parallel of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi>) and yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have 724625; the half is 362312 which is the Logarithm of the diffe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rence of Longitude in the Aequinoctia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> part of the Globe, 4200 <hi>m.</hi> D C de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>manded: So that the proportions A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rithmetical agree with the propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions Geometrical, therefore the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:135346:21"/> difference of Longitude in the middle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arallel of the Globe, is the proper <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ifference of Longitude 3093 <hi>m.</hi> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>roportion to the Rumb, by the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etick Compaſs.</p>
               <p>I have done with firſt Queſtionn in the Common Chart between places differing in Longitude and Latitude, wherein I have proved how the Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians and parallels of the common Chart differing in Longitude and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, are transferr'd by Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in proportion to the difference of Latitude, and the diſtance of places upon the Globe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſt of all,</hi> I ſhall ſhew you how to transferr the difference of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude in one and the ſame Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude in the Common Chart, into the Meridians and parallels of the Globe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>EXAMPLE.</label> In the Common Chart in the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of 50 <hi>d.</hi> 00 <hi>m.</hi> the difference of Longitude is 3093 <hi>m.</hi> L T, I demand
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:135346:22"/> the difference of Meridians in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Aequinoctial part of the Globe.</p>
               <p>To find the difference of Longitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in the Aequinoctial part of the Glo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the proportions Arithmetrical: <hi>As t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Co-ſine of the Latitude</hi> 40 d. 00 m. P 980806, <hi>is to the Logarithm of the diff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rence of Longitude, in the parallel</hi> 50 d. 00 m. L T, 3093 m. 349037 <hi>ſo is the Radius</hi> 90 d. P D, 1000000 <hi>to the Logarithm of</hi> 368231; <hi>which the Logarithm of</hi> D H, 4812 Miles, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 80 d. 12 m. <hi>the difference of Meridian in the Aequinoctial part of the Glob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> being oblique, do differ from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Meridians of the Common Chart tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are Right-lined; but the diſtance o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> places in the Globe are the ſame in the Common Chart, in regard the diſtance of places is transferr'd from the Common Chart to the Globe, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſuperficies of the Common Chart in all Meridians and parallels, is in proportion to the ſuperficies of the Globe in all Meridians and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallels.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:135346:22"/>
               <p>AND whereas all Writers in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation, have condemned the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ommon Chart to be peſtered with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>otorious errours, it proves a great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſtake; therefore I ſhall anſwer the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rincipal objection, and in that I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſwer all the reſt.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Edward Wright</hi> in his <hi>Correction of Errours in the Common Chart, Fol.</hi> 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aith, <q rend="inline">In ſhewing the diſtance of places, there is as great an errour committed as in any of the former.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>For Example,</label>If you imagine two Ships to be under the Aequinoctial 100 Leagues aſunder, and that each of them ſhould Sail from thence due North or South, under his Meridian, untill they come to the parallel of 60 <hi>d.</hi> Latitude, they ſhould be there but only 50 Leagues diſtant, becauſe at that Parallel, the Meridians are diſtant but half ſo much one from another, as they were at the Aequinoctial, as it may moſt mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:135346:23"/> appear by the Globe, and y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Chart will ſhew, that thoſe t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Ships have the ſelf-ſame diſtance 100 Leagues, being under the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rallel of 60 degrees, which they ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> before when they were under t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Aequinoctial.</p>
               <p>It is granted, that the difference <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Meridians in the Common Chart, 100 Leagues in the Equinoctial, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 100 Leagues in the Parallel of 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Degrees.</p>
               <p>In regard it appears by obſervatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by the Magnetick Compaſs, that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Eaſt and Weſt point of the Magnetic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Compaſs as it is Horizontal, does al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways point to the Poles of Eaſt and W. in the Celeſtial Sphere, likewiſe the North and South point of the Magne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Compaſs, as it is Horizontal, does always point to the Poles of North and South in the Celeſtial Sphere, in all Meridians and Parallels of the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtial Sphere, without making any difference of obſervation for the Semi-Diameter of the Earth: And whereas it appears by obſervation, that the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:135346:23"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>agnetick Compaſs in its true Poles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ill direct your the Circulation of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arth and Sea, in any Parallel of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atitude, keeping an equal diſtance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om the Poles of North and South; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> likewiſe it muſt be granted that the Meridians of the Magnetick Compaſs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſt run Parallel to the Poles of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſt and Weſt, the Circulation of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arth in all Parallel Meridians, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>egard the Magnetick Compaſs as it is Horizontal, makes the ſame poſition to the Poles of North and South in the Celeſtial Sphere, and to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oles of Eaſt and Weſt in the Celeſtial Sphere, in all Meridians and Parallels of the Terreſtial Sphere, without making any difference of obſervation for the Semi-Diameter of the Earth; So that the Meridians do croſs the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallels of the Magnetick Compaſs at Right-Angles, in all Meridians and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallels of the Earth and Sea, as it is by demonſtration in the Common Chart. Therefore the Magnetick Compaſs as it is Horizontal, muſt meaſure the ſuperficies of the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtial
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:135346:24"/> Sphere by Right-lines, as if t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Superficies of the Terreſtial Sphe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> was a plain to the Horizon; ſo that you imagine two Ships to be under t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Aequinoctial 100 Leagues aſunder, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that each of them ſhould Sail fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thence due North, or due South, und<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> his Meridian, untill they come to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Parallel of 60 <hi>d.</hi> Latitude, they mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> be 100 Leagues diſtant; in regard th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Meridians of the Magnetick Compaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> muſt run Parallel to the Poles o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Eaſt and Weſt, as the Eaſt and We<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> points of the Magnetick Compaſs ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Parallel to the Poles of North an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> South, I ſhall treat more at large o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this in its due place.</p>
               <p>I have given you the Geometrica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> demonſtration, and the Arithmetical rules, how all places in the Common Chart are transferr'd into the Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians and Parallels of the Globe; therefore you cannot reſolve any Queſtion in Navigaton from the Globe, without you have ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portions from the Globe as are in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion to the Rumb, and the Right-lines of the Magnetick Compaſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:135346:24"/>
               <head>The ſame Queſtion reſolved by <hi>Mercator's</hi> Projection.</head>
               <p>MR. <hi>Edward Wright</hi> in his <hi>Projection of Mercators Plain-Sphere,</hi> doth make the ſuperficies of the Globe as a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lain to the Horizon, and doth meaſure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l the Parallels of the Globe, in propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion to the degrees of the Aequinoctial <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the North and South Poles; ſo that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll the Parallels in <hi>Mercator</hi>'s Plain-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>phere, are of equal Diameter to the Poles. Then <hi>Mercator</hi> divides the Meridian Line into unequal parts, and doth increaſe the degrees and minutes of Latitude from the Aequinoctial to the Poles, to almoſt an endleſs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion: Therefore at every point of Latitude in his Plain-Sphere, the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Meridians doth ſo increaſe, that taking half a degree above a point of Latitude, and half a degree below the Latitude, that diſtance is to be a degree of Longitude in that Latitude; ſo that the deſign of <hi>Mercator</hi>'s Plain-Sphere is to meaſure the difference
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:135346:25"/> of Meridians, in proportion to the di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Meridians upon the Glo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>The Queſtion to be reſolved <hi>Mercator.</hi> The <hi>Lyzard,</hi> Latitude 50 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 00 <hi>m. Bermudus,</hi> Latitude 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their difference of Longitude in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Aequinoctial 70 <hi>d.</hi> 00 <hi>m.</hi> I demand t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Rumb by the Magnetick Compaſs.</p>
               <p>This Queſtion cannot be reſolved any Geometrical demonſtration, regard I have not the difference Longitude in proportion to the Rum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by the Magnetick Compaſs, for Right-lined Triangle muſt be of equ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> parts, otherwiſe the difference of L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>titude and the difference of Longitud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cannot be in proportion to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diſtance of places upon the Rum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by the Magnetick Compaſs, neithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> can this Queſtion be reſolved by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Arch of a great Circle, in regar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Angles of Poſition in all obliqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Angles, differ from the Angles of poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by the Magnetick Compaſs; ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that <hi>Mercator</hi> hath no way to find the Rumb from the Queſtion given, but brief Rules in Arithmetick, which are
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:135346:25"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ear a proportion to the Rumb by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Magnetick Compaſs, but when the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſtance between the Meridian and Parallel of the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> and the Meridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n and Parallel of <hi>Bermudus,</hi> and the difference of Longitude is required in a Right-lined Triangle, to be in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion to the Rumb, by the Magnetick Compaſs, and the difference of Latitude then all <hi>Mercator's</hi> brief Rules in Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dional parts, and the difference of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude in the Aequinoctial are rejected.</p>
               <p>TO reſolve the Queſtion by <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cators</hi> brief Rules, you muſt firſt find the Meridional parts contained between the difference of Latitudes.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>EXAMPLE.</label> The meridional parts contained in the Latitude of 50 <hi>d.</hi> 00 <hi>m.</hi> are 3475, the meridional parts contained in the Latitude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> are 2058, then Subtract the leſſer from the greater and you have 1417, the Meridional parts contained in the difference of Latitude; then multiply 70 <hi>d.</hi> 00 <hi>m.</hi> of Longitude by 60 <hi>m.</hi> and you have 4200 <hi>m.</hi> the difference of Longitude
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:135346:26"/> in the Aequinoctial. To find <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Rumb by <hi>Mercators</hi> brief Rules, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>As the Logarithm of the difference Latitude in Meridional parts,</hi> 1417 315136, <hi>is to the Radius</hi> 90 1000000; <hi>So is the Logarithm the difference of Longitude in the Aeq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noctial</hi> 4200 m. 362324, <hi>to the Ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gent of the Rumb</hi> 71 d. 21 m. 104718<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> So that <hi>Bermudus</hi> doth bear fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>Lyzard</hi> in an Angle of 71 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 21 <hi>m.</hi> South-Weſtwards: Add th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Radius to the difference of Longitud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the Aequinoctial, and Subtract th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Meridional parts contained in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> difference of Latitude, and you hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Tangent of the Rumb 71 <hi>d.</hi> 21 <hi>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 1047188.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Queſtion to be reſolved by <hi>Mercators</hi> brief Rules; the difference of Latitude between the <hi>Lyzard</hi> and <hi>Bermudus,</hi> in Meridional parts is 1417, and the Rumb is an Angle of 71 <hi>d.</hi> 21 <hi>m.</hi> South-Weſtwards, I demand the difference of Longitude in the Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinoctial.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:135346:26"/>
               <p>To find the difference of Longitude the Aequinoctial, ſay, <hi>As the Radius</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0 d. 1000000, <hi>is to the Logarithm of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e difference of Latitude in Meridional <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rts</hi> 1417, 315136; <hi>ſo is the Tangent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Rumb</hi> 71 d. 21 m. 1047171, <hi>to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Logarithm of the difference of Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ude in the Aequinoctial</hi> 4198 Miles, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>62307: Add the Logarithm of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eridional parts contained in the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ence of Latitude, to the Tangent of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Rumb, and Subtract the Radius, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd you have the Logarithm of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ifference of Longitude in the Aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>octial, 4198 <hi>m.</hi> 362307 demanded.</p>
               <p>The third Queſtion to be reſolved <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y <hi>Mercators</hi> brief Rules; the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Longitude in the Aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial, between the Meridian of the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> and the Meridian of <hi>Bermudus,</hi> 4200 <hi>m.</hi> The Rumb is an Angle of 71 <hi>d.</hi> 21 <hi>m.</hi> South-Weſtwards, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the difference of Latitude in Meridional parts.</p>
               <p>To find the difference of Latitude in Meridional parts, ſay, <hi>As the Tangent of the Rumb</hi> 71 d. 21 <hi>m.</hi> 1047171,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:135346:27"/> 
                  <hi>is to the Logarithm of the difference Longitude in the Aequinoctial</hi> 4200 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 362324; <hi>ſo is the Radius</hi> 90d. 100000<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>to the Logarithm of the difference <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Latitude in Meridional parts,</hi> 1417 315153: Add the Logarithm of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> difference of Longitude in the Aequ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noctial, to the Radius, and Subtrac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Tangent of the Rumb, and yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have the Logarithm of the differenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Latitude in Meridional parts, 1417 315153 demanded.</p>
               <p>The Fourth Queſtion to be reſolved by <hi>Mercator</hi>'s brief Rules. The diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Latitude as it is upon the Globe 1055 <hi>m.</hi> and the difference of Latitude in Meridional parts 1417; and the difference of Longitude in a Right-lined Triangle, according to the Rumb found by theſe brief Rules, 3126 <hi>m.</hi> I demand the difference of Longitude in the Aequinoctial.</p>
               <p>To find the difference of Longitude in the Aequinoctial, Say, <hi>As the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garithm of the difference of Latitude upon the Globe</hi> 1055 m. 302325; <hi>is to the Logarithm of the difference of Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:135346:27"/> in a Right-lined Triangle,</hi> 3126 <hi>m.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9498; <hi>ſo is the Logarithm of the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nce of Latitude in Meridional parts,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>17, 315136; <hi>to the Logarithm of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>fference of Longitude in the Aequinoctial</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>98, 362309: Add the Logarithm the difference of Longitude in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ght-lined Triangle, to the Logarithm <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the difference of Latitude in Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dional parts, and Subtract the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arithm of the difference of Latitude <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pon the Globe, and you have the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ogarithm of the difference of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tude in the Aequinoctial, 4198 <hi>m.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>62309, demanded.</p>
               <p>The fifth Queſtion to be reſolved by <hi>Mercator's</hi> brief Rules; The difference <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f Longitude in the Aequinoctial <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 200 <hi>m.</hi> and the difference of Latitude <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s it is upon the Globe 1055 <hi>m.</hi> and the difference of Latitude in Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dional parts 1417; I demand the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Longitude in a Right-lined Triangle. To find the difference of Longitude in a Right-lined Triangle, by <hi>Mercators</hi> brief Rules: Say, <hi>As the Logarithm of the difference of Latitude
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:135346:28"/> in Meridional parts</hi> 1417, 31513 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>to the Logarithm of the difference of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gitude in the Aequinoctial</hi> 420 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 362324; <hi>So is the Logarithm of difference of Latitude upon the</hi> (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 1055 m. 302325; <hi>to the Logarith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the difference of Longitude in a Ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>-lined Triangle,</hi> 3127, 349513: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Logarithm of the differenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Longitude in the Aequinoctial, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Logarithm of the difference of L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tude upon the Globe, and Subtract <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Logarithm of the difference of L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gitude in the Aequinoctial, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you have the Logarithm of the di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rence of Longitude in a Right-li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Triangle, 3127, 349513; deman<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>In the next place <hi>Mercator</hi> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> borrow the Rules of the Globe, find the difference of Meridians any one Parallel.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>EXAMPLE.</label> There are two Meridians differi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in Longitude 70 <hi>d.</hi> 00 <hi>m.</hi> in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinoctial, <hi>Bermudus,</hi> Latitude 32
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:135346:28"/> 25 <hi>m.</hi> I demand the difference of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>idians in the Latitude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>m.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o find the difference of Meridians <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ween 70 <hi>d.</hi> 00 <hi>m.</hi> of Longitude, in Latitude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25. <hi>m.</hi> Say, <hi>As Radius</hi> 90 d. 00 m. 1000000; <hi>is the Logarithm of</hi> 70 d. 00 m. <hi>or</hi> 00 m. 362324; <hi>So is the Co-ſine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Latitude of Bermudus</hi> 57 d. 35 m. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2643; <hi>to the Logarithm of</hi> 354967, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>545 <hi>m. or</hi> 59 d. 05 m. Add the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rithm of the difference of Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>de in the Aequinoctial, to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e of the Latitude, and Subtract the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>adius, and you have the Logarithm the difference of Meridians, in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>titude of <hi>Bermudus,</hi> 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4967; or 3545 <hi>m.</hi> or 59 <hi>d.</hi> 05 <hi>m.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>emanded.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſt of all,</hi> there are two Meridians <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iffering in Longitude 70 <hi>d.</hi> 00 <hi>m.</hi> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Aequinoctial; the <hi>Lyzard</hi> Latitude <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0 <hi>d.</hi> 00 <hi>m.</hi> I demand the difference <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f Longitude in the Latitude of 50 <hi>d.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To find the difference of Meridians <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etween 70 <hi>d.</hi> 00 <hi>m.</hi> of Longitude, in
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:135346:29"/> the Latitude of 50 <hi>d.</hi> oo <hi>m.</hi> Say <hi>the Radius</hi> 90 d. oo m. 1000000 <hi>to the Logarithm of</hi> 70 d. oo m 4200 m. 362324: <hi>So is the Co-ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Latitude of the</hi> Lyzard 40 d. oo 980806; <hi>to the Logarithm of</hi> 3431 <hi>or</hi> 2700 <hi>m. or</hi> 45 d. oo <hi>m.</hi> Add Logarithm of the difference of L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude in the Aequinoctial, to the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſine of the difference of Latitude, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Subtract the Radius, and your ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Logarithm of the difference Merdians in the Latitude of the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard,</hi> 50 <hi>d.</hi> oo <hi>m.</hi> 343130; or 2700 or 45 <hi>d.</hi> oo <hi>m.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have given you a full account all the brief Rules, by which <hi>Mercat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> doth pretend to perform the work Navigation, wherein you may obſerv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> there is not one Queſtion in all <hi>Merc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> brief Rules, that is in proportio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to the diſtance between the Meridia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Parallel of the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Meridian and Parallel of <hi>Bermudus</hi> therefore <hi>Mercators</hi> brief Rules are o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> no further uſe in Navigation, in regard the brief Rules are not in proportion
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:135346:29"/> the diſtance of places; ſo that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rk of Navigation cannot be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>med without thoſe Rules are in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>portion to a Geometrical demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ation.</p>
               <p>Then obſerve you cannot meaſure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e diſtance of places, differing in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ngitude and Latitude in <hi>Mercators</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ani-Sphere, in proportion to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſtance of places upon the Globe: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>herefore Mr. <hi>Edward Wright</hi> in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orrection of Errours in Navigation, <hi>page</hi> 59. ſaith, <hi>if two places differ ſo in Longitude as well as in Latitude, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ok how many degrees the difference of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atitude containeth; ſo many degrees of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Aequinoctial take with your Compaſs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd leading one foot in the Aequinoctial, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ove forward the other alſo Parallel-wiſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eeping always that diſtance, till it croſs the Rumb of thoſe two places, in ſuch ſort, that one Foot reſting in that croſſing, the other carried about may but touch the AEquinoctial, then take with your Compaſs the Segment or part of the Rumb, between that croſſing, and the Aequinoctial, ſet both Feet in the Aequinoctial, and ſee
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:135346:30"/> how many degrees are contained be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> them, for ſo many ſcore Leagues diſtance of thoſe two places.</hi> So you are to take with your Com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the difference of Latitude from Aequinoctial, which is of equal p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and run that Parallel to the Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>noctial, untill the other point <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> croſs the Rumb, then take the diſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from the point that croſſes the Ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to the place where the Rumb <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> croſs the Aeqinoctial, and meaſ that diſtance in the Aequinoct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> which is of equal parts for the diſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> between the <hi>Lyzard</hi> and <hi>Bermud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Therefore <hi>Mercator</hi> doth grant t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the difference of Latitude, and diſtance of Places, muſt be meaſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> by a Scale of equal parts, to be in p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion to the Rumb by the Magneti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Compaſs; this poſition agrees w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Common Chart: Then in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> plaineſt Rules of Art, the differen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of Latitude and the diſtance of Place being meaſured by a Scale of equ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> parts, the difference of Longitude mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> be of equal parts, in proportion to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:135346:30"/> difference of Latitude, and the diſtance places, in a Right-lined Triangle, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>erwiſe you muſt alter the Rumb the Magnetick Compaſs, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ance of places.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Mercator</hi> oppoſeth this poſition his Plani-Sphere, and from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ithmetical Rules of the Globe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erein the difference of Meridians <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ween the Meridian and Parallel of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ermudus,</hi> and the Meridian of the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>zard</hi> is 59 <hi>d.</hi> 05 <hi>m.</hi> likewiſe <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tor</hi> proves the difference of Meridians his Plani-Sphere, between the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dian and Parallel of <hi>Bermudus,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Meridian of the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> to be in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>roportion to the difference of Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ians upon the Globe, by taking half degree above the Latitude of <hi>Bermu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us,</hi> 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> and half a degree below the Latitude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> which diſtance is a degree of Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude in the Latitude of <hi>Bermudus,</hi> therefore ſo oft as you can have that diſtance between the Meridian of <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mudus,</hi> and the Meridian of the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> ſuch is the difference of Longitude
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:135346:31"/> 59 <hi>d.</hi> 05 <hi>m.</hi> Do the like, and you ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> have the difference of Meridian between places in any other Paralle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> upon <hi>Mercators</hi> Plani-Sphere, in pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>portion to the difference of Meridian between places in any Parallel of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Globe, ſo that the difference of Lon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gitude between the Meridian an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> parallel of <hi>Bermudus,</hi> and the Meri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dian of the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> is greater tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the diſtance, which is out of all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion in a Right-lined Triangle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Therefore <hi>Mercator</hi> hath no Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trical Demonſtration, either in oblique Angles or by Right-lined Angles, to prove the difference of Meridians, as it is upon the Globe, to be in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion to the difference of Latitude and the diſtance of places, and the Rumb by the Magnetick Compaſs.</p>
               <p>I have proved how the difference of Latitude, and the difference of Longitude, and the diſtance of places in the Common Chart, is transferred to be in proportion upon the Globe.</p>
               <p>I have proved how the difference of Longitude in all Right-lined Triangles,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:135346:31"/> is in proportion to the middle Parallel of all places upon the Globe, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Meridians of the Globe, as they are drawn, muſt differ from the Meridians of the Magnetick Compaſs; ſo that it is the principal point in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation, to enquire whether the North and South Points of the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netick Compaſs, run in the Meridians of the Globe, as they are drawn, or whether the North and South points of the Magnetick Compaſs, run parallel to the Poles of Eaſt and Weſt, as the Eaſt and Weſt points of the Magnetick Compaſs, run parallel to the Poles of North and South: Therefore I ſhall proceed to lay a Foundation in Naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that men may no longer halt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween three opinions, wherein I ſhall prove by obſervation and demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the Magnetick Compaſs, as it is Horizontal, that the North and South Points of the Magnetick Compaſs, run Parallel to the Poles of Eaſt and Weſt, as the Eaſt and Weſt points of the Magnetick Compaſs run Parallel to the Poles of North
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:135346:32"/> and South; ſo that the Common Chart that is ſo much rejected, is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> only Truth in Navigation.</p>
               <p>In the firſt place, I ſhall prove the Eaſt and Weſt Points of the Magnetick Compaſs, point to the Poles of Eaſt and Weſt in the Celeſtial Sphere, in all Meridians and Parallels of the Terreſtial Sphere; then I ſhall prove the Eaſt and Weſt Points of the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netick Compaſs run Parallel to the Poles of North and South, in all Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridians and Parallels of the Terreſtial Sphere.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>EXAMPLE.</label> By <hi>Obſervation,</hi> if the Sun be upon the Horizon in the Aequinoctial, the Suns-Amplitude ſhall be Eaſt or Weſt of you, by the Magnetick Compaſs, as it is Horizontal, in all Meridians and Parallels of the Terreſtial Sphere; but if I was in the Latitude, 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> or in any other Latitude, and I was to Sail by the Magnetick Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs Eaſt or Weſt, the Circulation of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:135346:32"/> the Earth and Sea, I ſhall find I have not altered my Latitude by obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; therefore the Eaſt and Weſt courſe of the Magnetick Compaſs agrees with the Parallels of Latitude upon the Terreſtial Sphere by obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; this poſition cannot be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, but from the Latitude of Places by obſervation, which agrees with the Eaſt and Weſt courſe of the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netick Compaſs; ſo that the Parallels of Latitude upon the Globe, are of equal diſtance from the Poles of North and South, and in proportion to the Rumb by the Magnetick Compaſs.</p>
               <p>In the next place, I ſhall prove the North and South Points of the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netick Compaſs, point to the Poles of North and South in the Celeſtial Sphere, in all Meridians and Parallels of the Terreſtial Sphere. Then I ſhall prove the North and South Points of the Magnetick Compaſs, muſt run parallel to the Poles of Eaſt and Weſt, in all Meridians and Parallels of the Terreſtial Sphere.</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:135346:33"/>
               <p>
                  <label>EXAMPLE.</label> By <hi>Obſervation,</hi> If the Sun or Star be upon their Meridian in my Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian and Parallel of the Terreſtia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sphere, the Sun's or Stars Azimuth muſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be North or South, by the Horizonta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bearing of the Magnetick Compaſs to the Celeſtial Poles; ſo that the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netick Compaſs, as it is Horizontal, points to the Celeſtial Poles of North and South, and to the Celeſtial Poles of Eaſt and Weſt, in all Meridians and Parallels of the Earth and Sea; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out giving any difference of obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the Semi-Diameter of the Earth and Sea, and notwithſtanding the Magnetick Compaſs points to the Celeſtial Poles of North and South, and to the Celeſtial Poles of Eaſt and Weſt, in all Meridians and Parallels of the Terreſtial Sphere, it is proved by obſervation, that you may run the Circulation of the Earth by the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netick Compaſs, in any Parallel of Latitude; therefore the Magnetick
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:135346:33"/> Compaſs muſt run Parallel to the Poles of Eaſt and Weſt, as the Magnetick Compaſs runs Parallel to the Poles of North and South in the Terreſtial Sphere, in regard the Magnetick Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs makes the ſame poſition to the Poles of Eaſt and Weſt, and to the Poles of North and South, in the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial Sphere; ſo that the difference of Meridians by the Magnetick Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, as it is Horrizontal upon the Terreſtial Sphere, is of equal diſtance from the Poles of Eaſt and Weſt, as the difference of the Parallels of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude by the Magnetick Compaſs, as it is Horizontal, is of equal diſtance from the Poles of North and South.</p>
               <p>This poſition muſt be infallible; for by obſervation, the Magnetick Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, as it is Horizontal, points to the Celeſtial Poles; ſo that the North and South points of the Magnetick Compaſs, do croſs the Eaſt and Weſt points of the Magnetick Compaſs, at Right-Angles, in all Meridians and Parallels of the Earth and Sea: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Magnetick Compaſs, doth
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:135346:34"/> meaſure the ſuperficies of the Glob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by Right-lines, as if the ſuperficies o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Globe was a Plain to the Horizon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>In the next place, if the Sun be i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Aequinoctial, and that you were i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Latitude of 60 <hi>d.</hi> or 70 <hi>d.</hi> or 80 <hi>d</hi> of North or South Latitude, the Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> upon the Horizon ſhall be Eaſt of you in the Morning, and Weſt of you i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Afternoon, by the Magnetick Compaſs, in its true Poles, as if you were in the Aequinoctial part of the Earth or Sea: The reaſon of this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation is this, the Terreſtial Sphere is ſpacious to us that are upon it, but it appears to be no other than a Center to the body of the Sun or Stars, in regard the Magnetick Compaſs runs atwhart the Parallels of Latitude in the Terreſtial Sphere, to the Poles of Eaſt and Weſt in the Celeſtial Sphere, without giving any difference of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation for the Semi-Diameter of the Earth and Sea: Therefore it had been impoſſible to find the Magnetick Compaſs ſhould run Parallel to the Poles of North and South in the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtial
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:135346:34"/> Sphere, if the Meridian Alti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the Sun or Stars, by obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, did not produce the ſame La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude or Parallel with the Magnetick Compaſs, the Circulation of the Earth, in regard the Magnetick Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, as it is Horinzontal, points to the Poles of Eaſt and Weſt in the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial Sphere, as the Magnetick Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs points to the Poles of North and South in the Celeſtial Sphere.</p>
               <p>Then obſerve, there is no reaſon in Navigation to ſuppoſe the Meridian, or the North and South Points of the Magnetick Compaſs, as it is Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zontal, to the Meridian Altitude of the Sun or Stars, in the Celeſtial Sphere, to run to the North and South Poles, as it is in the Terreſtial Sphere; but that you may likewiſe ſuppoſe Meridians, or the Eaſt and Weſt points of the Magnetick Compaſs, as it is Horizontal, to the Suns Ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude in the Aequinoctial, to run to the Poles of Eaſt and Weſt in the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtial Sphere; in regard the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netick Compaſs makes the ſame
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:135346:35"/> poſition, to the Poles of Eaſt and Weſt, as it has to the Poles of North and South in the Celeſtial Sphere.</p>
               <p>In the next place it muſt be granted if the Eaſt and Weſt points of the Magnetick Compaſs, in the Parallel o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 80 <hi>d.</hi> point to the Poles of Eaſt and Weſt in the Celeſtial Sphere; without giving any difference of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, for almoſt the Semi-Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meter of the Earth, in the Terreſtial Sphere, then the North and South Points of the Magnetick Compaſs, in the Meridian of 80 <hi>d.</hi> muſt point to the Poles of North and South in the Celeſtial Sphere, without giving any difference of obſervation, for almoſt the Semi-Diameter of the Earth, in the Terreſtial Sphere: Therefore the Meridians of the Magnetick Compaſs, hath the ſame poſition in the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtial Sphere, and muſt run Parallel to the Poles of Eaſt and Weſt, as the Parallels of Latitude run Parallel by the Magnetick Compaſs, to the Poles of North and South.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:135346:35"/>
               <p>Then obſerve the Magnetick Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, being always Horizontal to the Horizon, it doth meaſure the Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficies of the Earth and Sea by Right-lines, in the Parallel Meridians to the Poles of Eaſt and Weſt, and in the Parallels to the Poles of North and South, as if the Superficies of the Globe was a plain to the Horizon; this poſition you have at large in the Common Chart, wherein you have the difference of Meridians, and the difference of Latitude, and the diſtance of places in proportion to the Rumb, and the Right-lines of the Magnetick Compaſs.</p>
               <p>If the poſition of the Common Chart be not the only truth in Navi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, there is no Geometrical De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration in proportion to the Rumb, and the Right-lines of the Magnetick Compaſs.</p>
               <p>Therefore it hath been a great miſtake in all Writers, to ſuppoſe the Magnetick Compaſs to agree with the Meridians of the Globe as they are drawn; whereas, there is no obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:135346:36"/> or demonſtration to prove i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> only the Meridians of the Magnetic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Compaſs, as it is Horizontal to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Meridians of the Sun and Stars, poin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to the Poles of the Celeſtial Sphere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> To this I muſt reply, that the Ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and Weſt points of the Magnetic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Compaſs, as it is Horizontal, poin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to the Eaſt and Weſt Poles of the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial Sphere, from all Meridians an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Parallels of the Terreſtial Sphere; ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that you may as well draw Meridian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in Navigation by the Magnetick Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, from the Poles of Eaſt and Weſt as from the Poles of North and South in the Terreſtial Sphere; therefore the work of Navigation cannot be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by the oblique Lines of the Globe.</p>
               <p>I have proved by obſervation, that the Eaſt and Weſt points of the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netick Compaſs, run Parallel to the Poles of North and South in the Terreſtial Sphere, therefore the North and South points of the Magnetick Compaſs, muſt run Parallel to the Poles of Eaſt and Weſt in the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtial
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:135346:36"/> Sphere; in regard thoſe Poles do croſs at Right-Angles, in all Meridians and Parallels of the Earth and Sea.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſt of all,</hi> I ſhall ſhew you the errours that attend <hi>Mercator.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have proved that <hi>Mercator</hi> does grant the difference of Latitude, and the diſtance of places to be of equal parts, and to be in proportion to the Rumb by the Magnetick Compaſs in a Right-lined Triangle; ſo that <hi>Mercator</hi> hath granted three parts in four in a Right-lined Triangle; then if the difference of Longitude in a Right-lined Triangle, be not the true difference of Meridians, according to the Rumb by the Magnetick Compaſs, we have no Geometrical Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Navigation, therefore I ſhall proceed to find the diſtance between the Meridian and Parallel of <hi>Bermudus,</hi> and the Meridian and Parallel of the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> in a Right-lined Triangle, from the Rumb ſound by the brief Rules of <hi>Mercator,</hi> and the difference of Latitude.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:135346:37"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>And laſt of all,</hi> I ſhall ſhew you the diſproportion between the Meridians of the Common Chart, and the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridians of <hi>Mercator</hi> and the Globe, as they are drawn; ſo that whoever pretends to keep account of the Ships way, according to the difference of Meridians in <hi>Mercator</hi>'s Plani-Sphere, or according to the difference of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridians upon the Globe, they muſt commit groſs errours.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>EXAMPLE.</label> I Sail from the Meridian and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel of the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> in the Latitude of 50 <hi>d.</hi> 00 <hi>m.</hi> in an Angle of 71 <hi>d.</hi> 21 <hi>m.</hi> South-Weſtward: As the Rumb is found by the brief Rules of <hi>Merca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> into the Meridian and Parallel of <hi>Bermudus,</hi> in the Latitude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> I demand the diſtance and the difference of Longitude between the Meridian and Parallel of <hi>Bermudus,</hi> and the Meridian and Parallel of the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> in a Right-lined Triangle.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:135346:37"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>geometrical diagram</figDesc>
                  <head>Pag: 61</head>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:135346:38"/>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:135346:38"/>
               <p>The Angles of poſition by <hi>Merca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> brief Rules, do differ from the Angles of poſition by the Common Chart 11 <hi>m.</hi> however the diſtance between the <hi>Lyzard</hi> and <hi>Bermudus</hi> cannot be known, but by a Right-lined Triangle.</p>
               <p>The Angle following being a Right-lined Triangle, is in like proportion to the Common Chart, ſo is L the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian and Parallel of the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> and B is the Meridian and Parallel of <hi>Bermudus:</hi> Then is L A the difference of Latitude 1055 <hi>m.</hi> and C L D is the Rumb or Angle of poſition, between the Meridian and Parallel of the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> and the Meridian and Parallel of <hi>Bermudus,</hi> then is A B and L T the difference of Longitude between the Meridian of the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> and the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian of <hi>Bermudus,</hi> and L B is the diſtance between the <hi>Lyzard</hi> and <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mudus,</hi> then is B H and L Q the difference of Longitude in <hi>Mercators</hi> Plani-Sphere, and upon the Globe, which differs from the Meridians of the Common Chart 419 <hi>m.</hi> and 426 Miles.</p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:135346:39"/>
               <p>To find the diſtance between the Meridian and Parallel of the <hi>Lyzard</hi> and <hi>Bermudus,</hi> L B, the proportions Arithmetical: <hi>As the Co-ſine of the Rumb</hi> 71 d. 21 m. A B L, 950485; <hi>is to the Logarithm of the difference of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude</hi> 1055 m. L A, 302325: <hi>So is the Radius</hi> 90 d. LAB, 1000000; <hi>to the Logarithm of the diſtance</hi> 3299 m. L B; 351840 <hi>demanded:</hi> Add the Loga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rithm of the difference of Latitude to the Radius, and Subtract the Co-ſine of the Rumb, and you have the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garithm of the diſtance 351840, L B, 3299 <hi>m.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus you ſee when <hi>Mercator</hi> hath wearied himſelf with finding brief Rules, to be in proportion between the difference of Longitude in the Aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial, and the difference of Latitude in Meridional parts, to find the Rumb by the Magnetick Compaſs: Then <hi>Mercator</hi> doth grant that the diſtance of places differing in Longitude and Latitude, cannot be found by any Geometrical Demonſtration, to be in proportion to the Rumb by the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netick
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:135346:39"/> Compaſs, and the difference of Latitude, but by a Right-lined Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angle; therefore <hi>Mercator</hi> doth grant three parts in four in a Right-lined Triangle; then if the difference of Longitude in a Right-lined Triangle, be not the true difference of Meridians, there is no Geometrical Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Navigation, to find the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Meridians in proportion to the Rumb by the Magnetick Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs.</p>
               <p>In the next place I ſhall proceed to find the difference of Longitude in a Right-lined Triangle, from the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Latitude, and the Rumb found by <hi>Mercators</hi> brief Rules.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>EXAMPLE.</label> I Sail from the Meridian and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel of the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> in the Latitude of 50 <hi>d.</hi> 00 <hi>m.</hi> in an Angle of 71 <hi>d.</hi> 21 <hi>m.</hi> South-Weſtward: As the Rumb is found by the brief Rules of <hi>Mercator,</hi> into the Meridian and Parallel of <hi>Bermudus,</hi> in the Latitude of 32 <hi>d.</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:135346:40"/> 25 <hi>m.</hi> I demand the difference of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude in a Right-lined Triangle.</p>
               <p>To find the difference of Longitude the proportions Arithmetical: <hi>As the Radius</hi> 90 d. A B L, 1000000; <hi>is to the Logarithm of the difference of Latitude</hi> 1055 m. L A, 302325: <hi>So is the Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent of the Rumb</hi> 71 d. 21 m. A L B, 1047171; <hi>to the Logarithm of the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Longitude</hi> 349496, A B, 3126 <hi>m.</hi> Add the Logarithm of the difference of Latitude to the Tangent of the Rumb, and Subtract the Radius, and you have the Logarithm of the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Longitude, in proportion to the Rumb by the Magnetick Compaſs, and the difference of Latitude in a Right-lined Triangle.</p>
               <p>In the practical part of the Sea, the Rumb is always given, as in the firſt Queſtion in the Common Chart, 71 <hi>d.</hi> 10 <hi>m.</hi> So that the brief Rules of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator</hi> do alter the Rumb 11 <hi>m.</hi> which alters the difference of Longitude 33 <hi>m.</hi> and the diſtance 30 <hi>m.</hi> otherwiſe this latter Right-lined Triangle would
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:135346:40"/> agree with the former. I ſhall paſs by theſe ſmall errours, and proceed to the greater in <hi>Mercators</hi> Plani-Sphere, and upon the Globe, the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Longitude between the Meridian and Parallel of <hi>Bermudus,</hi> and the Meridian of the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> is proved to be 3545 <hi>m.</hi> B H, or 59 <hi>d.</hi> 05 <hi>m.</hi> and the difference of Longitude is proved to be 3126 <hi>m.</hi> B A, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Common Chart; ſo that the difference of Longitude in <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator</hi>'s Plani-Sphere, and upon the Globe, is more than the difference of Longitude in the Common Chart, by 419 <hi>m.</hi> A H; therefore, if I was to Sail from B to H, I muſt out-run the Meridian of the <hi>Lyzard</hi> in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Chart 419 <hi>m.</hi> before I can expect to arrive in the Meridian of <hi>Mercator,</hi> or the Meridian of the Globe: Then if I was to Sail from L to H by the Magnetick Compaſs, I muſt Sail in an Angle of 21 <hi>d.</hi> 40 <hi>m</hi> South-Eaſtward by the Magnetick Compaſs, to arrive in the Meridian of the Globe or <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator;</hi> ſo that I have ſhewed you how
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:135346:41"/> great the diſproportion is between the Meridians of the Common Chart, and the Meridians of <hi>Mercator,</hi> or the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridians of the Globe; therefore the Meridians of the Magnetick Compaſs were never rightly underſtood.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe in <hi>Mercators</hi> Plani-Sphere, and upon the Globe, the difference of Longitude between the Meridian and Parallel of the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> and the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian of <hi>Bermudus,</hi> is proved to be 2711 <hi>m.</hi> L Q, or 45 <hi>d.</hi> and the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Longitude is proved to be 3126, L T, according to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Chart; ſo that the difference of Longitude is <hi>Mercator</hi>'s Plani-Sphere, and upon the Globe is leſs than the difference of Longitude in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Chart, by 426 <hi>m.</hi> Q T; ſo that if I was to Sail from L to T, I muſt run 426 <hi>m.</hi> before I can arrive in the Meridian of <hi>Bermudus,</hi> in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Chart: Then if I was to Sail from B to Q, by the Magnetick Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, I muſt Sail in an Angle of 21 <hi>d.</hi> 59 <hi>m.</hi> North-Eaſtward, before I can arrive in the Meridian of the Globe
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:135346:41"/> or <hi>Mercator;</hi> ſo that I have ſhewed you how great the diſproportion is between the Meridians of the Common Chart, and the Meridians of <hi>Mercator,</hi> or the Meridians of the Globe; therefore the Meridians of the Magnetick Compaſs were never rightly underſtood, in regard there are ſuch various opinions in Navigation, and the diſproportion between one poſition and the other is ſo great, inſomuch that the Queſtion may be asked, what is truth in Navi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation?</p>
               <p>I have proved by Demonſtration and Obſervation, that the Magnetick Compaſs, as it is Horizontal, doth point to the Poles of Eaſt and Weſt in the Celeſtial Sphere, in all Meridians and Parallels of the Earth and Sea, without giving any difference of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation for the Semi-Diameter of the Earth: But by obſervation from the Meridian Altitude of the Sun and Stars, the Magnetick Compaſs doth run Parallel to the Poles of North and South in the Terreſtial Sphere, the Circulation of the Earth; therefore it
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:135346:42"/> had been impoſſible to prove the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netick Compaſs ſhould run Parallel to the Poles of North and South, in the Terreſtial Sphere; if the Magnetick Compaſs did not run Parallel to the Latitude of places by obſervation.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe, I have proved by Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation and Demonſtration, that the Magnetick Compaſs, as it is Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zontal, doth point to the Poles of North and South in the Terreſtial Sphere, in all Meridians and Parallels of the Earth and Sea, which Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians do croſs the Eaſt and Weſt Poles of the Magnetick Compaſs, as it is Horizontal to the Celeſtial Sphere, at Right-Angles, in all Meridians and Parallels in the World: Therefore the Meridians of the Magnetick Compaſs being Horizontal, muſt run Parallel to the Poles of Eaſt and Weſt in the Terreſtial Sphere, as the Magnetick Compaſs, being Horizontal, doth run Parallel to the Poles of North and South in the Terreſtial Sphere.</p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:135346:42"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſt of all,</hi> the Magnetick Compaſs being of Right-lines, doth meaſure the Superficies of the Globe by Right-lines, as if the ſuperficies of the Globe was always a plain to the Horizon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſo that whatever projection diſagree<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with the Rumb, and the difference o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Latitude, and the difference of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude, and the diſtance of places, as it is in proportion in a Right-lined Triangle, muſt be a falſe poſition in Navigation: therefore there is but one truth in Navigation, and that is the Common Chart, that hath been ſo much rejected by all Writers, for the Meridians and Parallels of places cannot be known upon the Globe or <hi>Mercators</hi> projection, but as it is transferred from the Common Chart, which is in proportion to a Right-lined Triangle.</p>
               <p>I ſhall proceed to the Arch of a great Circle, which is the third po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, or principal kind of Sailing ſo called, wherein I ſhall ſhew you, that the Queſtion cannot be given from the practical part of the Sea, but muſt
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:135346:43"/> alter the Meridian and Parallel of all places upon the Globe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>SAILING by the Arch of a great Circle.</head>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>The true diſtance between two places in the Arch of a great Circle, as in the following Rules.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. IF both places have no Latitude, as being under the Aequinoctial, and one of them no Longitude, then the Longitude of the other place is the diſtance: If it be not above 180 <hi>d.</hi> but if it be above 180 <hi>d.</hi> then Subtract it out of 360 <hi>d.</hi> the remainder is the diſtance.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If both places have Longitude under the Aequinoctial, the difference of Longitude is the diſtance, ſo it be under 180 <hi>d.</hi> but if it be above 180 <hi>d.</hi> then Subtract it out of 360 <hi>d.</hi> and the remainder is the difference of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude.</p>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:135346:43"/>
                  <p n="3">3. If both places have one and the ſame Meridian, and one of them have Latitude, then the Latitude is the diſtance.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. If both places have Latitude, as both Northerly or both Southerly, being under the ſame Meridian, the difference is the diſtance.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. If one place have North Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and the other South Latitude, being under the ſame Meridian, the ſum of both is the diſtance.</p>
                  <p>The Arch of a great Circle in the Terreſtial Globe, doth give a nearer diſtance of places than the Common Chart; ſo that the Arch of a great Circle does not run in the Parallels of the Globe, without it be in the Aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial: Likewiſe the Angles of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition in the Arch of a great Circle, do differ from the Angles of poſition by the Magnetick Compaſs; inſomuch that the Queſtion cannot be given from the Rumb by the Magnetick Compaſs, in the practical part of the Sea, but you muſt alter the Meridian and Parallel of all places in the Globe.</p>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:135346:44"/>
                  <p>
                     <label>EXAMPLE.</label> There are two places in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel of 50 <hi>d.</hi> that differ in Longitude 70 <hi>d.</hi> in the Aequinoctial, I demand the Angle of poſition, and the diſtance.</p>
                  <p>The Demonſtration follows, E F D the Aequinoctial, L C B the Paralle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of Latitude 50 <hi>d.</hi> L Q B the neareſt diſtance, L Q half the neareſt diſtance, E L the Latitude 50 <hi>d.</hi> L P the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement of the Latitude 40 <hi>d.</hi> E P D the Angle at the Pole, or the difference of Longitude in the Aequinoctial, 70 <hi>d.</hi> E P F the Angle of half the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Longitude 35 <hi>d.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>To find the diſtance.</head>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>geometrical diagrams</figDesc>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Pag:</hi> 72.</head>
                  </figure>
                  <p>From hence you may obſerve that the Arch of a great Circle doth not run in the Parallel of Latitude by Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, L C B, but doth run in an Arch of a nearer diſtance, as L Q B, for it is proved the difference of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude upon the Globe, in the Parallel of 50 <hi>d.</hi> L C B, is 45 <hi>d.</hi> or 2700 M. and by the Arch of a great Circle, the diſtance L Q B, is 43 <hi>d.</hi> 16 <hi>m.</hi> or 2596 <hi>m.</hi> So that the Arch of a great Circle doth differ from the diſtance of places in the Parallels of the Globe, I <hi>d.</hi> 44 <hi>m.</hi> or 104 Miles, which muſt alter the Latitude by obſervation, and the Rumb by the Magnetick Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs.</p>
                  <p>In the next place I ſhall find the Angle of poſition by the Arch of a great Circle, the Queſtion requires
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:135346:46"/> another demonſtration, before I can reſolve the Queſtion as in the adjacent figure.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>To find the Angle of poſition.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>As the Sine of</hi> 50 <hi>d.</hi> L E, 988425; <hi>is to the Tangent of</hi> 55 d. E G, 1015477; <hi>So is the Radius</hi> 90 d. L H, 1000000; <hi>to the Tangent of</hi> 1027052, H L A, 61 d, 48 m. <hi>and is equal to the Angle</hi> B L P, 61 <hi>d.</hi> 48 m. <hi>which is the Angle of poſition, to the Arch of a great Circle</hi> L Q B. Add the Tangent 55 <hi>d.</hi> E G, to the Radius 90 <hi>d.</hi> L H, and Subtract the Sine of 50 <hi>d.</hi> L E, and you have the Tangent of the Angle H L A, 1037052, 61 <hi>d.</hi> 48 <hi>m.</hi> demanded.</p>
                  <p>Then Obſerve, if you Sail in an Angle of 61 <hi>d.</hi> 48 <hi>m.</hi> North-Weſt-ward, by the Magnetick Compaſs, from L, you cannot arrive at Q or B, in regard you cannot Sail from one place to another in the ſame Parallel, without you Sail Eaſt or Weſt by the Magnetick Compaſs; ſo that the Arch of a great Circle runs in a nearer
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:135346:46"/> diſtance than the Parallel of Latitude: Therefore you cannot Sail by the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netick Compaſs from the Latitude of 50 <hi>d.</hi> L, into the Latitude of 50 <hi>d.</hi> B, in an Angle of 61 <hi>d.</hi> 48 <hi>m.</hi> in the Arch of a great Circle L Q B.</p>
                  <p>But it may be Objected, that I may alter my Courſe to arrive at B. If ſo, then I muſt alter the Queſtion. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuppoſe the Queſtion to be this, I have Sailed from the Latitude of 50 <hi>d.</hi> L, in angle of 61 <hi>d.</hi> 48 <hi>m.</hi> North-Weſt-ward, 400 <hi>m.</hi> I demand in what Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian and Parallel of the Globe I am in. I have proved I cannot Sail in an Angle of 61 <hi>d.</hi> 48 <hi>m.</hi> from the Latitude of 50 <hi>d.</hi> L, by the Magnetick Compaſs, and in the Arch of a great Circle LQB, ſo as to arrive in the Latitude of 50 <hi>d.</hi> at B; then is it impoſſible for me to know in what Meridian and Parallel of the Globe I am, in regard the Magnetick Compaſs does not run in the Arch of a great Circle: Therefore I muſt reſolve the Queſtion by a Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lined Triangle, and transferr the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian and Parallel of places found in a
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:135346:47"/> Right-lined Triangle, into the Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian and Parallel of the Globe; ſo that you cannot perform the work of Navigation by the Oblique Lines of the Globe, in the Arch of a great Circle: In regard the Oblique Lines of the Globe differ from the Rumb, and the Right-Lines of the Magnetick Compaſs, inſomuch that you cannot give the Queſtion from the practical part of the Sea, to be in proportion to the Angles of poſition, and the diſtance of places in the Arch of a great Circle, but you muſt alter the Meridian and Parallel of places in the Globe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>I ſhall add one Example more from the foregoing Queſtion, between the <hi>Lyzard</hi> and <hi>Bermudus.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The <hi>Lyzard</hi> in the Latitude of 50 <hi>d.</hi> E L, <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rmudus</hi> in the Latitude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> F B; their difference of Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude in the Aequinoctial 70 <hi>d.</hi> E P F. I demand the Angles of poſition E L B, and L B P, and their diſtance L B, in an Arch of a great Circle.</p>
                  <p>The demonſtration follows, E F the Aequinoctial, C B the Parallel of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:135346:47"/> the Latitude of <hi>Bermudus,</hi> L A the Parallel of the Latitude of the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> E P F the Angle at the Pole, or the difference of Longitude in the Aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial 70 <hi>d.</hi> L P the Complement of the Latitude of the <hi>Lyzard</hi> 40 <hi>d.</hi> B P the Complement of the Latitude of <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rmudus</hi> 37 <hi>d.</hi> 35. <hi>m.</hi> L B the diſtance between the Meridian and Parallel of the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> and the Meridian and Parallel of <hi>Bermudus,</hi> then is the Angle E L B, the Angle of poſition between the <hi>Lyzard</hi> and <hi>Bermudus,</hi> and the Angle L B P, is the Angle of poſition between <hi>Bermudus</hi> and the <hi>Lyzard.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This Queſtion requires a further Demonſtration, before we can find Arithmetical proportion, as in the adjacent figure, and in the firſt place we are to find the ſide P A; then ſay, <hi>As the Sine of</hi> 20 d. G E, 953405; <hi>is to the Tangent of</hi> 50 d. E L, 1007618: <hi>So is the Radius</hi> 90 d. G F. 1000000; <hi>to the Tangent of</hi> 1054213, F A, 73 d. 59 m. <hi>whoſe Complement is</hi> 16 d. 01 m. A P: <hi>Then Subtract</hi> A P, 16 d. 01 <hi>m. out of</hi> P B, 57 d. 35 m. <hi>and you have</hi>
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:135346:48"/> 41 d. 34 m. A B. Add the Tangent of 50 <hi>d.</hi> E L, to the Radius 90 <hi>d.</hi> G F, and Subtract the Sine of the 20 <hi>d.</hi> G E, and you have the Tangent of 73 <hi>d.</hi> 59 <hi>m.</hi> F A, whoſe Complement is A P, 16 <hi>d.</hi> 01 <hi>m.</hi> demanded.</p>
                  <p>Now to find the diſtance you have the ſide A P, 16 <hi>d.</hi> 01 <hi>m.</hi> and the ſide L P, 40 <hi>d.</hi> and the ſide A B, 41 <hi>d.</hi> 34 <hi>m.</hi> I demand the diſtance L B.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>As the Co-ſine of</hi> 16 d. 01 m. A P, 998280; <hi>is to the Co-ſine of</hi> 40 d. L P, 988425: <hi>So is the Co-ſine of</hi> 41 d. 34 m. A B, 987400; <hi>to the Co-ſine of</hi> 977545, L B, 53 d. 24 <hi>m.</hi> the diſtance between the Meridian and Parallel of the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> and the Meridian and Parallel of <hi>Bermudus</hi> by the Arch of a great Circle, but by the Common Chart the diſtance is 3268 <hi>m.</hi> or 54 <hi>d.</hi> 28 <hi>m.</hi> which is 64 <hi>m.</hi> or 01 <hi>d.</hi> 04 <hi>m.</hi> more than the diſtance by the Arch of a great Circle.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>geometrical diagrams</figDesc>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Pag:</hi> 78</head>
                  </figure>
                  <p>
                     <hi>As the Sine of the ſide</hi> LB, 53 <hi>d.</hi> 24 <hi>m.</hi> 990461; <hi>is to the Sine of the Angle</hi> LPB, 70 d. 00 m. 997298: <hi>So is the Sine of the ſide</hi> P B, 57 <hi>d.</hi> 35 <hi>m.</hi> 992643; <hi>to the Sine of the Angle of poſition between the</hi> Lyzard <hi>and</hi> Bermudus 999480, C L B, 81 d. 10 m. <hi>South-Weſtwards.</hi> So that the Angle of poſition in the Arch of a great Circle, doth differ from the Angle of poſition by the Magnetick Compaſs in the Common Chart 10 <hi>d.</hi> 00 <hi>m.</hi> Then if I ſhould Sail in the Angle of 80 <hi>d.</hi> 10 <hi>m.</hi> by the Magnetick Compaſs, from the <hi>Lyzard</hi> L, towards <hi>Bermudus</hi> B, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not arrive at <hi>Bermudus,</hi> in regard the Angle of poſition by the Arch of a great Circle, doth differ from the Angle of poſition by the Magnetick Compaſs 10 <hi>d.</hi> 00 <hi>m.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Laſt of all,</hi> I ſhall find the Angle of poſition from <hi>Bermudus</hi> to the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> P B L, the ſide P B is 57 <hi>d</hi> 35 <hi>m.</hi> the Angle C L B is 81 <hi>d.</hi> 10 <hi>m.</hi> the ſide P L is 40 <hi>d.</hi> 00 <hi>m.</hi> I demand the Angle
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:135346:50"/> of poſition from <hi>Bermudus</hi> to the <hi>Lyzard</hi> P B L.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>As the ſine of the ſide</hi> P B, 57 d. 35 m. 992643; <hi>is to the Sine of the Angle</hi> C L B, 81 d. 10 m. 999481: <hi>So is the Sine of the ſide</hi> L P, 40 <hi>d.</hi> 980806; <hi>to the Sine of the Angle of poſition from</hi> Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mudus <hi>to the</hi> Lyzard 987644, P B L, 48 d. 48 m. <hi>North-Eaſtwards.</hi> Add the Sine of the Angle C L B, 81 <hi>d.</hi> 10 <hi>m.</hi> to the Sine of the ſide L P, 40 <hi>d.</hi> and Subtract the Sine of the ſide P B, 57 <hi>d.</hi> 35 <hi>m.</hi> and you have the Sine of the Angle of poſition from <hi>Bermudus</hi> to the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> in the Arch of a great Circle 987644, P B L, 48 <hi>d.</hi> 48 <hi>m.</hi> North-Eaſtwards; ſo that the Angle of poſition in the Arch of a great Circle, differs from the oppoſite Angle of poſition by the Magnetick Compaſs, in the ſame Queſtion 39 <hi>d.</hi> 58 <hi>m.</hi> for the Angle of poſition from the <hi>Lyzard</hi> to <hi>Bermudus</hi> is 81 <hi>d.</hi> 10 <hi>m.</hi> South-Weſtward, and the Angles of poſition from <hi>Bermudus</hi> to the <hi>Lyzard</hi> is 48 <hi>d.</hi> 48 <hi>m.</hi> North-Eaſtward; then by the Common Rules in Navigation, if I
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:135346:50"/> Sail by the Magnetick Compaſs from the <hi>Lyzard</hi> to <hi>Bermudus,</hi> in an Angle of 81 <hi>d.</hi> 10<hi>m.</hi> South-Weſtward, 3204 M. and was to return to the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> I muſt Sail in an Angle of 08 <hi>d.</hi> 50 <hi>m.</hi> Eaſt-Northwards by the Magnetick Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, in regard 08 <hi>d.</hi> 50 <hi>m.</hi> is the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite point to 81 <hi>d.</hi> 10 <hi>m.</hi> Likewiſe if I Sail by the Magnetick Compaſs from <hi>Bermudus</hi> to the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> in an Angle of 48 <hi>d.</hi> 48<hi>m.</hi> North-Eaſtward 3204 M. and was to return to <hi>Bermudus,</hi> I muſt Sail in an Angle of 41 <hi>d.</hi> 12 <hi>m.</hi> Weſt-Southward.</p>
                  <p>Then Obſerve, ſuch is the diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion in the Angles of poſition in the Arch of a great Circle, that it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to Sail by the Magnetick Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs in the Arch of a great Circle, and in the Angles of poſition found in the Arch of a great Circle, into the ſame Meridian and Parallel of places upon the Globe, in regard the Angles of poſition in the Arch of a great Circle, does differ from the Angles of poſition by the Magnetick Compaſs.</p>
                  <p>But it may be Objected, that I may
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:135346:51"/> alter my Courſe to arrive at my Port. If ſo, you muſt alter the Queſtion, for by the Angles of poſition in the Arch of a great Circle, you cannot tell where you are upon the Globe; in regard the Angles of poſition in the Arch of a great Circle, does differ from the Angles of poſition by the Magnetick Compaſs, for the Angle of poſition in the Arch of a great Circle, is 81 <hi>d.</hi> 10 <hi>m.</hi> South-Weſtward from the <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard</hi> to <hi>Bermudus,</hi> and it is 48 <hi>d.</hi> 48 <hi>m.</hi> North-Eaſtward from <hi>Bermudus</hi> to the <hi>Lyzard;</hi> and by the Magnetick Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs I muſt Sail in an Angle of 71 <hi>d.</hi> 10 <hi>m.</hi> South-Weſtward from the <hi>Lyzard</hi> to <hi>Bermudus,</hi> and I muſt Sail in an Angle of 18 <hi>d.</hi> 50 <hi>m.</hi> Eaſt-North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward from <hi>Bermudus</hi> to the <hi>Lyzard;</hi> ſo the oppoſite point of the Magnetick Compaſs, muſt be the Angle of poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to return to the ſame Port, or the Magnetick Compaſs is of no uſe in Navigation; ſo that I cannot give the Queſtion from the Practical part of the Sea, to be reſolved by the Arch of a great Circle, but I muſt alter
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:135346:51"/> the Meridian and Parallel of places in the Globe, therefore you muſt reſolve the Queſtion from the Angle of poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by the Magnetick Compaſs, and the difference of Latitude in the practical part of the Sea, by a Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lined Triangle, and transferr the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian and Parallel of places found in a Right-lined Triangle, into the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian and Parallel of the Globe, as I have already ſhewed; ſo that the work of Navigation muſt be reſolved by the Rumb, and the Right-lines of the Magnetick Compaſs in a Right-lined Triangle, before the Meridian and Parallel of places can be known upon the Globe.</p>
                  <p>Notwithſtanding the Arch of a great Circle will not anſwer the deſign of Navigation by the Magnetick Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs; it muſt be granted, that the Arch of a great Circle in the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtial Sphere, and in the Celeſtial Sphere is a true poſition, in regard the Angles of poſition in all Oblique An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles, are in proportion to the ſeveral ſides of all Oblique Angles, which
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:135346:52"/> is the neareſt diſtance of places.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>EXAMPLE.</label> If I obſerve the diſtance of two Stars, in one and the ſame Parallel, I do meaſure the neareſt diſtance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween thoſe two Stars, but I cannot meaſure the extream Arch of that Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel by obſervation; ſo that the neareſt diſtance is the Arch of a great Circle, by obſervation and demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Likewiſe all obſervations in the Arch of a great Circle gives the neareſt diſtance; ſo that the Arch of a great Circle does not run in the Parallels of the Globe, without it be in the Aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial, to the Poles of North and South, and in the Ecliptick, which is as the Aequinoctial to the Poles Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, and upon the Horizon, which is as the Aequinoctial to the Zenith; therefore the Angles of poſition found in the Arch of a great Circle, in any Parallel of Latitude, is not to be mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured by any Geometrical meaſure upon the Terreſtial or Celeſtial Sphere, without it be at the North or South
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:135346:52"/> Poles the meaſure of thoſe Angles are in the Aequinoctial, or at the Poles Ecliptick the meaſure of thoſe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles are in the Ecliptick Line, or at the Poles of your Zenith, or point over your head, the meaſure of thoſe Angles are in the Horizon. In this caſe the Angles make a Right-Angle in the Aequinoctial, and in the Zodiack, and in the Horizon, but in all other Angles of poſition, they are not to be mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured Geometrically upon the Globe; ſo that ſuch Angles, are only in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion to the ſides of an Oblique Angle, which is the neareſt diſtance of places upon the Globe; therefore thoſe Angles are out of all proportion to the Rumb, and the Right-Lines of the Magnetick Compaſs; ſo that the work of Navigation, cannot be performed by the Arch of a Great Circle.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To Conclude,</hi> I have proved how all the known part of the World is laid down in the Meridians and Parallels of the Common Chart, in proportion to the Rumb, and the Right-lines of the Magnetick Compaſs.</p>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:135346:53"/>
                  <p>I have proved how the Meridians and Parallels of all places in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Chart are transferred into the Meridians and Parallels of the Globe; in regard the difference of Meridians upon the Globe, does increaſe from the Poles to the Aequinoctial, and the difference of Meridians in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Chart, which is in proportion to the Rumb, and the Right-lines of the Magnetick Compaſs, are of equal diſtance, ſo that the difference of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridians upon the Globe being Oblique, are out of all proportion to the Rumb and the Right Lines of the Magnetick Compaſs, without it be in the middle Parallel of places differing in Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and Latitude.</p>
                  <p>It is proved, <hi>Mercator</hi> divides his Plani-Sphere in proportion to the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Meridians upon the Globe: Therefore the Meridians of <hi>Mercator</hi> does not run in the Meridians of the Magnetick Compaſs, or the Meridians of the Common Chart, in regard the difference of Meridians upon <hi>Mercators</hi> Plani-Sphere, does increaſe from the Poles to the Aequinoctial, and the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:135346:53"/> of Meridians in the Common Chart, which is in proportion to the Rumb, and the Right-lines of the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netick Compaſs are of equal diſtance, which leads me to this conſideration; all points of the Magnetick Compaſs, as they are drawn, are of Right-lines, therefore the North and South point of the Magnetick Compaſs, does croſs the Eaſt and Weſt point of the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netick Compaſs at Right-Angles; ſo that it is proved by Obſervation, that the Eaſt and Weſt point of the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netick Compaſs, will direct you the Circulation of the Earth and Sea, in all Parallels of Latitude; then obſerve the North and South point of the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netick Compaſs as it is drawn, doth croſs the Eaſt and Weſt point of the Magnetick Compaſs at Right-Angles, in all Meridians and Parallels of the Earth and Sea. Therefore the difference of Meridians by the Magnetick Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, muſt run Parallel in all Meridians and Parallels of the Earth and Sea, in proportion to the difference of the Parallels of Latitude, otherwiſe you may as well ſay the North and South
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:135346:54"/> point of the Magnetick Compaſs, as it is drawn, doth not croſs the Eaſt and Weſt point of the Magnetick Compaſs at Right-Angles.</p>
                  <p>I have proved by Obſervation, that the Meridians of the Magnetick Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, doth croſs the Eaſt and Weſt points of the Magnetick Compaſs at Right-Angles, in all Meridians and Parallels of the Earth and Sea; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Meridians of the Magnetick Compaſs, muſt run Parallel to the Poles of Eaſt and Weſt, as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallels of the Magnetick Compaſs run Parallel to the Poles of North and South, ſo that the Common Chart is the only Truth in Navigation, in regard it is in proportion to the Rumb, and the Right-lines of the Magnetick Compaſs, therefore the Magnetick Compaſs doth meaſure the ſuperficies of the Globe by Right-lines, as if the ſuperficies of the Globe was a plain to the Horizon.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THere will be Publiſhed the <hi>Practical part of the Sea,</hi> with ſome Queſtions in <hi>Aſtronomy,</hi> uſeful in <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation,</hi> by the ſame Author.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:135346:54"/>
            <head>APPENDIX.</head>
            <p>THE foregoing Treatiſe is onely upon a ſingle Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion in the three principal kinds of Sailing, ſo called, proving that the work of Navigation cannot be performed by the <hi>Arch</hi> of a <hi>great Circle,</hi> or by <hi>Mercator</hi>'s Poſition; and that the <hi>Common Chart</hi> that hath been ſo much rejected, is the <hi>onely truth</hi> in Navigation, in regard it is in proportion to the <hi>Rumb</hi> and the <hi>right lines</hi> of the Magnetick Compaſs; therefore I ſhall Illuſtrate this Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the Common Chart by a double Queſtion in the practical part of the Sea, comparing it with the ſame Queſtion by <hi>Mercator</hi>'s Poſition; wherein the <hi>defect</hi> of <hi>Mercator</hi>'s Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition will more plainly appear, than in a ſingle Queſtion.</p>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:135346:55"/>
            <p>Before I proceed to give this Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, I ſhall ſhew you by what <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical Queſtions</hi> at Sea the work of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation is performed by the <hi>Common Chart,</hi> and by <hi>Mercator.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, by the <hi>Common Chart;</hi> if you have daily Obſervation, then you have the difference of Latitude and the Rumb rectified to all impediments to find the diſtance and the difference of Longitude in a right-lined Triangle.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Mercator;</hi> if you have daily Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, then you have the difference of Latitude in Meridional parts, and the Rumb rectified to all impediments to find the difference of Longitude in the Equinoctial.</p>
            <p>The Second Queſtion in the Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal part of the Sea by the <hi>Common Chart;</hi> if you have no Obſervation for many days, and that you have run ſeveral traverſes, then you have your daily diſtance run by your Log, and the Rumb rectified to all impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments upon each traverſe, to find the difference of Latitude, and the difference of Longitude; this traverſe
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:135346:55"/> is called <hi>a dead reckoning;</hi> but as ſoon as you have Obſervation, having as before allowed for all impediments of the Rumb in your daily traverſe, and that you find the Ship <hi>before</hi> your Obſervation, or <hi>aſtern</hi> of your Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, then you muſt add or ſubtract by a due proportion to each diſtance run by your Log, ſo as to fall into your Latitude by Obſervation: The ſeveral traverſes being thus reſolved, you muſt find the difference of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude, and the diſtance, and the Rumb upon which you have made your way from your laſt Obſervation in a right-lined Triangle, which is in propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Rumb and the right lines of the Magnetick Compaſs.</p>
            <p>The Second Queſtion in the Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal part of the Sea by <hi>Mercator.</hi> If you have no Obſervation for many days, and that you have run ſeveral traverſes, then you have your daily diſtance run by your Log, and the Rumb rectified to all impediments up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on each traverſe, to find the difference of Longitude in the Equinoctial; this
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:135346:56"/> traverſe is called a <hi>dead reckoning.</hi> Here you may obſerve <hi>Mercator</hi>'s brief Rules are not in proportion to the Rumb and Diſtance in a right-lined Triangle; therefore <hi>Mercator</hi> muſt take the Latitude of places as they are found in each traverſe in a right-lined Triangle, then <hi>Mercator</hi> has the Meridional parts contained in the difference of Latitude, and the Rumb in each right-lined Triangle, to find the difference of Longitude in the Equinoctial, which muſt be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded or ſubtracted, as you increaſe or leſſen the Degrees of Longitude in the Equinoctial, until you come to ſhape a direct Courſe to your Port, according to <hi>Mercator</hi>'s Poſition, by a right-lined Triangle.</p>
            <p>In the laſt place, having made ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral traverſes in the Sea, if you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to know a direct Courſe from your Ship to your Port in the <hi>Common Chart,</hi> you have the difference of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude between the Ship in the Sea and your Port; and the difference of Longitude between your Ship in the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:135346:56"/> Sea and the Port you are to ſail to, to find the Rumb and Diſtance upon a direct Courſe to your Port by a right-lined Triangle.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Mercator,</hi> having made ſeveral traverſes in the Sea, if you deſire to know a direct Courſe to your Port, you have the difference of Latitude in Meridional parts between your Ship in the Sea and your Port, and the difference of Longitude in the Equinoctial between your Ship in the Sea, and the Port you are to ſail to, to find the Rumb and Diſtance upon a direct Courſe to your Port by a right-lined Triangle.</p>
            <p>Having given you this <hi>general</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Practical part of the Sea by the <hi>Plain Chart,</hi> and by <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator</hi>'s Projection, I ſhall proceed to the <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Two Ships Sail from the</hi> Lyzard <hi>in the Latitude of</hi> 50 d. <hi>the firſt Ship Sails in an Angle of</hi> 71 d. 10 m. <hi>South-weſtwards</hi> 3268 <hi>miles; the ſecond Ship Sails Weſt North-weſt</hi> 2400 <hi>miles. I demand the Rumb or Courſe, and the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:135346:57"/> diſtance that the ſecond Ship muſt ſail to arrive at the Port of the firſt Ship.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>By the Common Chart.</head>
               <p>The Queſtion of the firſt Ship is reſolved by demonſtration in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Figure: The <hi>Lyzard</hi> Latitude 50 <hi>d.</hi> I ſail in an Angle of 71 <hi>d.</hi> 10 <hi>m.</hi> South-Weſtwards, A L B, 3268 miles L B. I demand the difference of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, and the difference of Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude? I anſwer, I find my difference of Latitude to be 1055 miles in the Latitude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> L A. and my difference of Longitude to be 3093 miles, A B, which is the Meridian and Parallel of <hi>Bermudus</hi> in the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Chart:</hi> I have reſolved the <hi>Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metical</hi> part of this Queſtion in the firſt part of this ſmall Treatiſe, which is in like proportion with the <hi>Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trical</hi> part.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>geometrical diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>The Queſtion of the ſecond Ship in her firſt traverſe reſolved Arithmeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, to find the difference of Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, ſay, <hi>As the Radius</hi> 90 d. <hi>L D C,</hi> 1000000, <hi>is to to the Logarithm of the diſtance L C,</hi> 2400 <hi>miles,</hi> 338021; <hi>ſo is the ſine of the Rumb</hi> 67 d. 30 m. <hi>D L C</hi> 996561, <hi>to the Logarithm of the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Longitude</hi> 334582, <hi>or</hi> 2217 <hi>miles demanded.</hi> Add the ſecond and third Numbers in all Queſtions, as I have given them, and you ſhall have the Sine, or the Tangent, or the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garithm of the Numbers required.</p>
               <p>The Queſtion of the ſecond Ship in her firſt traverſe reſolved Arithmeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, to find the difference of Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, ſay, <hi>As the Radius</hi> 90 d. <hi>L D C</hi>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:135346:59"/> 1000000, <hi>is to the Logarithm of the diſtance</hi> 2400 <hi>miles L C,</hi> 338021, <hi>ſo is the co-ſine of the Rumb</hi> 67 <hi>d.</hi> 30 m. <hi>D L C</hi> 958283, <hi>to the Logarithm of the difference of Latitude</hi> 296304, <hi>or</hi> 918 <hi>miles L D.</hi> which agrees with the former demonſtration.</p>
               <p>The Queſtion of the ſecond Ship in her ſecond traverſe is reſolved by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration in the following Figure. In the firſt place, you muſt ſubtract the difference of Longitude the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Ship has made upon a Weſt North-weſt Courſe D C 2217, from the difference of Longitude between the <hi>Lyzard</hi> and <hi>Bermudus</hi> A B 3093 miles, and you have E B 876 miles, that your Ship is to the Eaſtward of the Meridian of <hi>Bermudus;</hi> then add the difference of Latitude L D 918, to the difference of Latitude between the <hi>Lyzard</hi> and <hi>Bermudus</hi> L A 1055 miles, and you have 1973 miles D A, equal to C E, the difference of Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude between the Ship and the Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of <hi>Bermudus.</hi> Then the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion ſtands thus in proportion, you
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:135346:59"/> have the difference of Longitude be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Ship and <hi>Bermudus</hi> E B 876 miles, and the difference of Latitude between the Ship and the Latitude of <hi>Bermudus</hi> 1973 miles C E. I demand the Rumb and Diſtance I have to ſail to <hi>Bermudus?</hi> I anſwer, I find the Rumb to be in an Angle of 23 <hi>d.</hi> 56 <hi>m.</hi> E C B South-weſtwards, and I find the diſtance to be 2159 miles CB; ſo that the ſecond Ship is arrived in the Meridian and Parallel of <hi>Bermu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> by Demonſtration, demanded.</p>
               <p>The Queſtion of the ſecond Ship in her ſecond traverſe reſolved Arithme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically; to find the Rumb, ſay, <hi>As the Logarithm of the difference of Latitude</hi> 1937 <hi>miles C E</hi> 329512, <hi>is to the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius</hi> 90 d. <hi>C B E</hi> 1000000; <hi>ſo is the Logarithm of the difference of Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude</hi> 876 <hi>miles E B</hi> 294250, <hi>to the tangent of the Rumb</hi> 964738 <hi>E C B</hi> 23 d. 56 m. So that your Courſe from your Ship to <hi>Bermudus</hi> is in an Angle of 23 <hi>d.</hi> 56 <hi>m.</hi> South-weſtward, demanded.</p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:135346:60"/>
               <p>The Queſtion of the ſecond Ship in her ſecond traverſe reſolved Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metically, to find the diſtance, ſay, <hi>As the Sine of the Rumb</hi> 23 d. 56 m. <hi>E C B.</hi> 960817; <hi>is to the Logarithm of the difference of Longitude</hi> 876 <hi>miles E B</hi> 294250; <hi>ſo is the Radius</hi> 90 d. <hi>C E B</hi> 1000000 <hi>to the Logarithm of the diſtance</hi> 333433 <hi>C B</hi> 2159 <hi>miles,</hi> the diſtance between the Ship in the Sea and <hi>Bermudus,</hi> demanded.</p>
               <p>Then Obſerve, I have reſolved the Queſtion of the firſt Ship ſailing from the <hi>Lyzard</hi> to <hi>Bermudus</hi> Geometri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally and Arithmetically, all which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſitions are in proportion in a right-lined Triangle to the Rumb and the right lines of the Magnetick Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs and the Common Chart. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe I have reſolved the Queſtion of the ſecond Ship in a traverſe from the <hi>Lyzard</hi> to <hi>Bermudus</hi> Geometrically and Arithmetically; all which Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are in proportion in right-lined Triangles to the Rumb, and the right lines of the Magnetick Compaſs and the Common Chart. So that the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:135346:60"/> ſecond Ship is arrived in the Meridian and Parallel of <hi>Bermudus.</hi> Therefore the ſecond Ship in her traverſe has not altered the difference of Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude in the Equinoctial of the firſt Ship, as it was tranſferred from the Common Chart to the Globe, or <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſame Queſtion reſolved by <hi>Mercator.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I have given you a general account of the practical part of the Sea by the <hi>Common Chart,</hi> and by <hi>Mercator;</hi> ſo that all traverſes muſt be reſolved in proportion to the Rumb and the right lines of the Magnetick Compaſs, I ſhall proceed to the Queſtion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Two Ships ſail from the</hi> Lyzard <hi>in the Latitude of</hi> 50 d. <hi>the firſt Ship ſails in an Angle of</hi> 71 d. 10 m. <hi>South-weſtwards</hi> 3268 <hi>miles; the ſecond Ship ſails Weſt North weſt</hi> 2400 <hi>mil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s. I demand the Rumb and the Diſtance that the ſecond Ship muſt ſail to arrive at the Port of the firſt Ship.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:135346:61"/>
               <p>Before I can reſolve this Queſtion by <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rcator</hi>'s brief Rules, to find the difference of Longitude in the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial, I muſt ſee what Latitude is in proportion to the Rumb and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the firſt Ship as it is found in a right-lined Triangle, in regard <hi>Mercator</hi>'s brief Rules are not in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion to the Rumb and the Diſtance of places, then the Queſtion ſtands thus.</p>
               <p>The Queſtion of the firſt Ship to be reſolved by <hi>Mercator</hi>'s brief Rules, the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> Latitude 50 <hi>d. Bermudus,</hi> La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> the Rumb is an Angle of 71 <hi>d.</hi> 10 <hi>m.</hi> South-weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards: I demand the difference of Longitude in the Equinoctial?</p>
               <p>To find the difference of Longitude in the Equinoctial, ſay, <hi>As the Radius</hi> 90 d. 1000000, <hi>is to the difference of Latitude in Meridional parts</hi> 1417: 315136, <hi>ſo is the tangent of the Rumb</hi> 71 <hi>d.</hi> 10 m. 1046714, <hi>to the Loga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rithm of the difference of Longitude in the Equinoctial</hi> 4155, 361850, <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:135346:61"/>
               <p>The Queſtion of the ſecond Ship in her firſt traverſe reſolved by <hi>Mercator</hi>'s brief Rules; before I can reſolve this Queſtion, I muſt ſee what Latitude is in proportion to the Rumb and Diſtance of the ſecond Ship in her firſt traverſe in a right-lined Triangle, in regard <hi>Mercator</hi>'s brief Rules are not in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion to the Rumb and Diſtance; then the Queſtion ſtands thus:</p>
               <p>The <hi>Lyzard</hi> Latitude 50 <hi>d.</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Ship in her firſt traverſe, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude 65 <hi>d.</hi> 18 <hi>m.</hi> the Rumb Weſt North-weſt, or in an Angle of 67 <hi>d.</hi> 30 <hi>m.</hi> I demand the difference of Longitude in the Equinoctial?</p>
               <p>To find the difference of Longitude in the Equinoctial, ſay, <hi>As the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius</hi> 90 d. 1000000, <hi>is to the Loga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rithm of the difference of Latitude in Meridional parts,</hi> 1747, 324229; <hi>ſo is the tangent of the Rumb</hi> 67 d. 30 m. 1038277, <hi>to the Logarithm of the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of Longitude in the Equinoctial</hi> 362502, <hi>or</hi> 4217 <hi>miles, demanded.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Queſtion of the ſecond Ship in her ſecond traverſe reſolved by <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator</hi>'s
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:135346:62"/> brief Rules: In the firſt place, you muſt obſerve, by the firſt traverſe of the ſecond ſhip the difference of Longitude in the Equinoctial is 4217 miles; therefore you muſt ſubtract the difference of Longitude in the Equinoctial (of the firſt ſhip) 4155 miles, and you have 62 miles, that the ſecond ſhip in her ſecond traverſe is to the Weſtward of the Meridian of <hi>Bermudus</hi> in the Equinoctial, then the Queſtion ſtands thus:</p>
               <p>The ſecond ſhip in her ſecond tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe is in the Latitude of 65 <hi>d.</hi> 18 <hi>m.</hi> ſhe is to ſail into the Latitude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> the whole difference of Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude in the Equinoctial between the ſecond ſhip in her ſecond traverſe and <hi>Bermudus</hi> is 62 miles Eaſt. I demand the Rumb or Courſe, and the diſtance the ſecond ſhip in her ſecond traverſe muſt ſail, to arrive at the Port of the firſt ſhip?</p>
               <p>To find the Rumb, ſay, <hi>As the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garithm of the difference of Latitude in Meridional parts</hi> 3164, 350023, <hi>is to the Radius</hi> 1000000, <hi>ſo is the Loga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rithm
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:135346:62"/> of the whole difference of Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude in the Equinoctial</hi> 62 <hi>miles,</hi> 179239, <hi>to the tangent of the Rumb</hi> 829216, <hi>or</hi> 01 d. 07 m. So that I am to ſail in an Angle of 01 <hi>d.</hi> 07 <hi>m.</hi> South-Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward from the place of my ſhip in her laſt traverſe, to arrive at <hi>Bermudus:</hi> Then obſerve, <hi>Mercator</hi> has altered the Rumb from that of the <hi>Common Chart</hi> 25 <hi>d.</hi> 03 <hi>m.</hi> To prove it, add 01 <hi>d.</hi> 07 <hi>m.</hi> that the ſecond ſhip in her ſecond traverſe ſails by <hi>Mercator</hi> South-Eaſtward into the Latitude of <hi>Bermudus,</hi> to 23 <hi>d.</hi> 56 <hi>m.</hi> that the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſhip in her ſecond traverſe has ſailed South-Weſtward upon the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Chart</hi> to <hi>Bermudus,</hi> and you have 25 <hi>d.</hi> 03 <hi>m.</hi> that the Rumb differs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Common Chart</hi> and <hi>Mercator;</hi> theſe are <hi>groſs errors</hi> in Navigation, therefore I ſhall ſhew you wherein <hi>Mercator</hi> commits them.</p>
               <p>In the next place, I ſhall reſolve the remaining part of <hi>Mercator</hi>'s Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation by right-lined Triangles in proportion to the Rumb found by <hi>Mercator</hi>'s brief Rules; for all tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſes
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:135346:63"/> muſt be reſolved by the Rumb and the right lines of the Magnetick Compaſs, in regard <hi>Mercator</hi>'s brief Rules are not in proportion to the Rumb and the diſtance ſailed; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe you cannot tell upon what Rumb or Courſe you have ſailed from your firſt Port upon a traverſe, or upon what Rumb or Courſe you are to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to your Port, or to any other part of the World: Then obſerve, if the Rumb and the difference of Latitude found by <hi>Mercator</hi> in a traverſe by the ſecond Ship, does not make out the ſame Rumb and diſtance that the firſt Ship made from the <hi>Lyzard</hi> to <hi>Bermudus,</hi> then it muſt be granted that <hi>Mercator</hi>'s brief Rules have led you into groſs Errors; this I ſhall prove from the Practical part of the Sea.</p>
               <p>I ſhall not be tedious, therefore I ſhall give the Queſtions reſolved.</p>
               <p>By <hi>Mercator,</hi> the firſt Ship ſails from the <hi>Lyzard</hi> in the Latitude of 50 <hi>d.</hi> at L, in an Angle of 71 <hi>d.</hi> 10 <hi>m.</hi> A L B, South-weſtwards 3268 miles L B; I
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:135346:63"/> demand the difference of Latitude, and the difference of Longitude in a right-lined Triangle? I anſwer, I find my dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of Latitude 1055 miles, and to be in the Latitude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> L A; and I find my difference of Longitude 3093 miles A B, demanded.</p>
               <p>By <hi>Mercator,</hi> the ſecond Ship in her firſt traverſe ſails from the <hi>Lyzard</hi> in the Latitude of 50 <hi>d.</hi> at L, in an Angle of 67 <hi>d.</hi> 30 <hi>m.</hi> D L C, North-weſtward 2400 miles L C. I demand the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of Latitude, and the difference of Longitude in a right-lined Triangle? I anſwer, I find my difference of Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude 918 miles, and to be in the Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of 65 <hi>d.</hi> 18 <hi>m.</hi> L D; and I find my difference of Longitude 2217 miles D C, demanded.</p>
               <p>By <hi>Mercator,</hi> the ſecond Ship in her ſecond traverſe ſails from the Latitude of 65 <hi>d.</hi> 18 <hi>m.</hi> at C, in an Angle of 01 <hi>d.</hi> 07 <hi>m.</hi> South-eaſtwards Q C E, into the Latitude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> Q C. I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the diſtance ſailed, and the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of Longitude in a right-lined Triangle? I anſwer, I find the diſtance
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:135346:64"/> C Q 1974 miles; and I find my dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of Longitude Q E, 39 miles Eaſt, demanded.</p>
               <p>Then ſubtract the difference of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude of the ſecond Ship in her ſecond traverſe Q E 39 miles, from the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of Longitude of the ſecond ſhip in her firſt traverſe D C 2217 miles, in regard the ſecond Ship in her ſecond traverſe is gone to the Eaſtward, and you have 2179 miles Q A, the difference of Longitude the ſecond Ship has made from the <hi>Lyzard</hi> into the Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of <hi>Bermudus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then ſubtract the difference of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude the ſecond Ship has made from the <hi>Lyzard</hi> into the Latitude of <hi>Bermu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> Q A 2179 miles, from the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Longitude the firſt Ship has made to <hi>Bermudus</hi> in the Latitude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> A B 3093 miles, and you have 914 Q B, or 15 <hi>d.</hi> 14 <hi>m.</hi> that <hi>Mercator</hi> is to the Eaſtward of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian and Parallel of <hi>Bermudus,</hi> when <hi>Mercator</hi> expects to be in the Meridian and Parallel of <hi>Bermudus.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:135346:64"/>
               <p>In the laſt place, you have the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of Latitude between the <hi>Lyzard</hi> and <hi>Bermudus</hi> L A 1055 miles, and the difference of Longitude 2179 miles A Q; I demand the Rumb and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance the ſecond Ship has ſailed from the <hi>Lyzard</hi> into the Latitude of <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mudus</hi> upon a direct Courſe? I anſwer, I have ſailed in an Angle of 64 <hi>d.</hi> 10 <hi>m.</hi> A L Q. South-weſtward; and I find my diſtance ſailed 2421 miles L Q demanded; at which place <hi>Mercator</hi> expects to be in the Meridian and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel of <hi>Bermudus;</hi> then ſubtract the Rumb of the ſecond ſhip from the <hi>Lyzard</hi> upon a direct Courſe A L Q 64 <hi>d.</hi> 10 <hi>m.</hi> when <hi>Mercator</hi> expects to be in the Meridian and parallel of <hi>Bermudus,</hi> from the Rumb of the firſt ſhip from the <hi>Lyzard</hi> to <hi>Bermudus</hi> A L B, 71 <hi>d.</hi> 10 <hi>m.</hi> and you have 07 <hi>d.</hi> 00 <hi>m.</hi> that the Angle of the poſition does differ between the firſt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſhip; then ſubtract the diſtance of the ſecond ſhip L Q 2421 miles, from the diſtance of the firſt ſhip L B 3268 miles, and you have
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:135346:65"/> 847 miles, that the ſecond ſhip does differ from the firſt ſhip; likewiſe ſubtract the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of Longitude at the ſecond ſhip 2179 miles A Q, from the difference of Longitude of the firſt ſhip 3093 miles A B, and you have 914 mile<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, or 15 <hi>d.</hi> 14 <hi>m.</hi> that the ſecond ſhip is to the Eaſtward of <hi>Bermudus</hi> in the Latitude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> Theſe are the groſs Errors that attend <hi>Mercator</hi>'s Poſition; for all traverſes by <hi>Mercator</hi> in the practical part of the Sea, muſt be reſolved by right-lined Triangles, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe you cannot give any account of the Rumb and the diſtance, and the difference of Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude your ſecond ſhip has made from her firſt Port, or that you can give any account upon what Rumb you are to return to your Port, or to direct your courſe to any other Port, if you do not reſolve all traverſes by the Rumb and the right lines of the Magnetick Compaſs in right-lined Triangles; therefore it muſt be granted, that I am to find the difference of Longitude in the Equinoctial that the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſhip has made in her traverſe from the <hi>Lyzard</hi> to be in proportion to the Rumb up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a direct Courſe by <hi>Mercator.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the laſt place, I muſt find the difference of Longitude in the Equinoctial that the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſhip has made upon a direct Courſe from the <hi>Lyzard</hi> into the Latitude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> In the laſt Queſtion, the Rumb is found to be in an Angle of 64 <hi>d.</hi> 10 <hi>m.</hi> South-weſtward
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:135346:65"/> that the ſecond ſhip has made in her tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe from the <hi>Lyzard</hi> upon a direct Courſe into the Latitude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> then you have the Latitude of the <hi>Lyzard</hi> 50 <hi>d.</hi> and the Latitude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> and the Rumb 64 <hi>d.</hi> 10 <hi>m.</hi> South-weſtward; I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the difference of Meridians in the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial that the ſecond ſhip has made from the <hi>Lyzard</hi> into the Latitude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m?</hi> I anſwer, the difference of Meridians in the Equinoctial is found to be 2926 miles, when <hi>Mercator</hi> expects to be in the Meridian of the Equinoctial equal to the firſt ſhip; then ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract the difference of Meridians in the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial of the ſecond ſhip 2926 miles, from the difference of meridians of the firſt ſhip in the Equinoctial 4155 miles, and you have 1229 miles, or 20 <hi>d.</hi> 29 <hi>m.</hi> that the ſecond ſhip is Eaſt of the firſt ſhip in the Equinoctial, when <hi>Mercator</hi> expects to be in the meridian of the Equinoctial with the firſt ſhip; ſo that <hi>Mercator</hi> hath altered the Rumb, and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and the difference of meridians of the ſecond ſhip in a right-lined Triangle, and in the Equinoctial, from the Rumb, and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and the difference of meridians of the firſt ſhip in a right-lined Triangle, and in the Equinoctial: So that to know the difference of Longitude in the Equinoctial is no way <hi>uſeful</hi> in Navigation, either upon the Globe, or upon <hi>Mercator</hi>'s Plani-Sphere.</p>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:135346:66"/>
               <p>I have proved by the <hi>Common Chart,</hi> that the ſecond ſhip making a traverſe, is arrived in the meridian of the firſt ſhip, and has not altered the meridian of the firſt ſhip in the <hi>Common Chart,</hi> or in the Equinoctial, as it is transferred to the Globe: I have ſatisfied the World that the <hi>Common Chart</hi> in the Practical part of the Sea, is the only <hi>true Chart</hi> in Navigation; if otherwiſe, I deſire to be better informed: Therefore it muſt be granted, that the Magnetick Compaſs as it is <hi>Horizontal,</hi> runs parallel to the <hi>Poles</hi> of <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt,</hi> as it runs parallel to the <hi>Poles</hi> of <hi>North</hi> and <hi>South,</hi> and is as much in proportion by <hi>Obſervation</hi> and <hi>Demonſtration</hi> to thoſe Poles, as the Poles <hi>Ecliptick</hi> are in <hi>proportion</hi> to any Queſtion in <hi>Aſtronomy.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="addenda">
            <pb n="111" facs="tcp:135346:66"/>
            <head>Addenda.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>The following Treatiſe will prove <hi>Mercator</hi>'s practical Rules in Navi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, to be notoriouſly falſe.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe Longitude not to be found by Obſervation, from the Celeſtial Bodies, without it be when Eclipſes appear in the Equinoctial.</p>
               <p>Laſt of all, the Earth is proved to be the Centre of the Starry Heaven.</p>
               <p>All which is proved by Obſervation and Demonſtration.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THE laſt Appendix to the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Treatiſe was a Queſtion given me, the Anſwer I gave to it, I thought ſufficient to have given ſatisfaction to any reaſonable Men, wherein I prove the Work of Naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion cannot be performed by <hi>Mercator</hi>'s brief Rules; but finding Mr. <hi>Flamſteed</hi> and other of our Shore Navigators to diſcourſe in Company in deriſion of
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:135346:67"/> what I have offered publickly to the World; I muſt tell him, it is not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming a Man of his Quality, but I hope this following Tratiſe may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce Mr. <hi>Flamſteed</hi> and the reſt, to let the World ſee ſome of their skill in Navigation, and to doe me ſo much right as to allow or diſprove what I have offered that Men may not halt between Opinions; however I ſhall make ſome ſmall alteration in the Queſtion in the foregoing Appendix, and give the Queſtion more Practical in Navigation, wherein all Men that are Studious in Navigation may give an Anſwer to all Objections any man ſhall propoſe, in oppoſition to what I have offered: for the Rules of Naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are Demonſtrative, and the Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metical Rules muſt be in proportion, otherwiſe ſuch Rules muſt be rejected; therefore I ſhall reſolve the following Queſtion by the Plain Chart, and by <hi>Mercator,</hi> wherein I ſhall ſhew you how far <hi>Mercator</hi>'s brief Rules are in proportion in each Traverſe to the Rumb, and the Right-lines of the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:135346:67"/> Magnetick Compaſs: then I ſhall ſhew you in the following Queſtion, wherein <hi>Mercator</hi>'s Practical Rules in Naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion do diſagree with the Rumb and the Right-lines of the Magnetick Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, by which <hi>Mercator</hi> pretends to Navigate; which will prove <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator</hi>'s Poſition in the Practical Parts of Navigation to be notorious falſe; as likewiſe are all thoſe that are of his perſuaſion, without they will ſatisfie the World to the contrary. Laſtly, as the Meridian and Parallel of all the known part of the World cannot be found in the practical part of Navigation, by the Arch of great Circle, or by <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator</hi>'s brief Rules, ſo likewiſe the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian and Parallel of places cannot be transferred from the Common Chart to the Globe, but onely from one Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian and Parallel of the Common Chart by ſuch Demonſtrations; you ſhall have the ſame Latitude and Diſtance of places to all the known Parts of the World, upon the Globe as it is transferred from onely one Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian and Parallel of the Common Chart
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:135346:68"/> to the Globe: otherwiſe the Meridian and Parallell of places cannot be known upon the Globe as they are found by the Practical part of Navigation. All which I ſhall prove at large.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Queſtion given is as following.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>EXAMPLE.</label> Two Ships ſail from the <hi>Lyzard</hi> in the Latitude of 50 <hi>d.</hi> the firſt Ship ſails in an Angle of 71 <hi>d.</hi> 10 <hi>m.</hi> South-Weſtward 3268 miles; the ſecond Ship ſails in an Angle of 67 <hi>d.</hi> 30 <hi>m.</hi> North-Weſtward 2400 miles, then the ſecond Ship ſails in an Angle of 23 <hi>d.</hi> 56 <hi>m.</hi> South-weſt-ward 2159 miles, I demand the difference of Longitude in each right lined Triangle, and the Latitude the firſt and ſecond Ship was in upon each Rumb and diſtance ſailed; and the difference of Longitude in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinoctial contained in each right lined Triangle.</p>
               <p>This Queſtion muſt be reſolved by right lined Triangles, which are in
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:135346:68"/> proportion with the Common Chart, otherwiſe the Latitude upon each di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance runn cannot be known, in regard <hi>Mercator</hi>'s brief Rules are not in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion to the Rumb, and the diſtance of places, therefore I ſhall give you the Queſtion reſolved by right lined Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angles in the Practical part of the Sea, according to the Common Chart, and proceed to <hi>Mercator</hi>'s brief Rules in the Practical part of the Sea.</p>
               <p n="1">I. The firſt Ship ſails from the <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard</hi> in the Latitude of 50 <hi>d.</hi> L in an Angle of 71 <hi>d.</hi> 10 <hi>m.</hi> South-weſt-ward, A L B, 3268 miles, L B. I find my difference of Latitude 1055 miles, South, and to be in the Latitude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> L A, likewiſe I find my difference of Longitude to be 3093 miles, Weſt A B, which is the Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian and Parallel of <hi>Barmudas</hi> upon the Common Chart, to which the Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metical Rules are in proportion.</p>
               <p n="2">II. The ſecond Ship in her firſt Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe ſails from the <hi>Lyzard</hi> in the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:135346:69"/> of 50 <hi>d.</hi> L, in an Angle of 67 <hi>d.</hi> 30 <hi>m.</hi> D L C, 2400 miles L. C. I find my difference of Latitude to be 918 miles, North L D, and to be in the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of 65 <hi>d.</hi> 18 <hi>m.</hi> at C, likewiſe I find my difference of Longitude to be 2217 miles Weſt D C, demanded, to which the Arithmetical Rules are in proportion.</p>
               <p n="3">III. The ſecond Ship in her ſecond Traverſe ſails from C, in the Latitude of 65 <hi>d.</hi> 18 <hi>m.</hi> in an Angle of 23 <hi>d.</hi> 56 <hi>m.</hi> South-weſt-wards E C B, 2159 miles C B, I find my difference of Latitude to be 1973 miles South, and to be in the Latitude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> at B, likewiſe I find my difference of Longitude to be 876 miles Weſt, E B, demanded, to which the Arithmetical rules are in proportion.</p>
               <p>To ſumm up the Practical part of Navigation, according to the Common Chart, and to give you the Meridian and Parallel of the ſecond Ship in her firſt and ſecond Traverſe; firſt you muſt add the difference of Longitude the ſecond Ship made in her ſecond
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:135346:69"/> Traverſe, 876 miles, E B, to the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of Longitude the ſecond Ship made in her firſt Traverſe 2217 miles, D C, and you have 3093 miles, A B, the difference of Longitude of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Ship in her firſt and ſecond Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe from the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> where ſhe meets the firſt Ship in the Latitude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> which is the Meridian and Parallel of the ſecond Ship in her firſt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Traverſe. See the Demonſtration which is according to the Common Chart.</p>
               <p>Having found the Latitudes and the difference of Longitudes in each right lined Triangle that the firſt and ſecond Ship was in, upon each Traverſe according to the plain Chart, I ſhall proceed to ſhew you how far <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator</hi>'s brief Rules are in proportion to the Rumb and the right lines of each right lined Triangle, in the foregoing Queſtion, Then I ſhall ſhew you wherein <hi>Mercator</hi>'s Practical Rules in Navigation diſagree.</p>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:135346:70"/>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>By <hi>MERCATOR.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p> In the firſt place, I ſhall ſhew you that the Rumb and the difference of Latitude in Meridional parts is in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion to the difference of Longitude in the Equinoctial in each right lined Triangle: In the next place, I ſhall ſhew you that the Meridional parts contained in the difference of Latitude and the difference of Longitude in the Equinoctial, and the difference of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude is in proportion to the difference of Longitude in each right lined Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angle, of the foregoing Queſtion: In the third place, I ſhall ſhew you that <hi>Mercator</hi>'s Practical Rules in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation do diſagree with the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Rules of <hi>Mercator,</hi> in each Traverſe; In regard the difference of Latitude in Meridional parts from the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> to the ſecond Ship in her ſecond Traverſe, and the difference of Longitude in the Equinoctial found according to <hi>Mercator</hi>'s Practical Rules in Navigation, and the difference of
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:135346:70"/> Latitude between the ſecond Ship in her ſecond Traverſe from the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> doth not give the ſame difference of Longitude, in a right lined Triangle from the <hi>Lyzard</hi> to the ſecond Ship in her ſecond Traverſe, in proportion to the difference of Longitude, found in each ſingle Traverſe in a right lined Triangle. This being proved, <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator</hi>'s Practical Rules in Navigation muſt be notorious falſe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Queſtions to be Reſolved by <hi>Merca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi>'s brief Rules, are as followeth.</head>
               <p n="1">
                  <label>EXAMPLE.</label> 1. To find the difference of Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude in the Equinoctial, in proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the foregoing Queſtion, The firſt Ship ſails from the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> in the Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of 50 <hi>d.</hi> L, in an Angle of 71 <hi>d.</hi> 10 <hi>m.</hi> A L B, South-weſt-ward into the Latitude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> at B. I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the difference of Longitude in the Equinoctial.</p>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:135346:71"/>
               <p>To Reſolve this Queſtion, ſay as the <hi>Radius</hi> 90 <hi>d.</hi> 1000000 is to the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garithm of the difference of Latitude in Meridional parts 1417, 315136, ſo is the Tangent of the Rumb, 71 <hi>d.</hi> 10 <hi>m.</hi> 1046714, to the Logarithm of the difference of Longitude in Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial 361850 or 4155 miles, or 69 <hi>d.</hi> 15 <hi>m.</hi> demanded.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To find the difference of Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude in the Equinoctial, in proportion to the foregoing Queſtion, the ſecond Ship ſails from the <hi>Lyzard</hi> in the Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of 50 <hi>d.</hi> L in an Angle of 67 <hi>d.</hi> 30 <hi>m.</hi> D L C North-weſt-ward into the Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of 65 <hi>d.</hi> 18 <hi>m.</hi> at C. I demand the difference of Longi. in the Equinoctial.</p>
               <p>To Reſolve this Queſtion, ſay as the <hi>Radius</hi> 90 <hi>d.</hi> 1000000 is to the Loga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rithm of the difference of Latitude in Meridional parts, 1748, 324254, So is the Tangent of the Rumb, 67 <hi>d.</hi> 30 <hi>m.</hi> 1038277, to the Logarithm of the difference of Longitude in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinoctial 362531, or 4220 miles or 70 <hi>d.</hi> 20 <hi>m.</hi> demanded.</p>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:135346:71" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p n="3">3. To find the difference of Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude in the Equinoctial, in proportion to the foregoing Queſtion, the ſecond Ship in her ſecond Traverſe ſails from C, in the Latitude of 65 <hi>d.</hi> 18 <hi>m.</hi> in an Angle of 23 <hi>d.</hi> 56 <hi>m.</hi> E C B, South-weſt-wards, into the Latitude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 15 <hi>m.</hi> I demand the difference of Longitude in the Equinoctial.</p>
               <p>To Reſolve this Queſtion, ſay as the <hi>Radius</hi> 90 <hi>d.</hi> 1000000 is to the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garithm of the difference of Latitude in Meridional parts 3165, 350037. So is the Tangent of the Rumb, 23 <hi>d.</hi> 56 <hi>m.</hi> 964722, to the Logarithm of the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of Longitude in the Equinocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, 314759, or 1405 miles, or 22 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> demanded.</p>
               <p>To ſumm up the Practical part of the ſecond Ship, in her firſt and ſecond Traverſe, according to <hi>Mercator,</hi> you muſt add the difference of Longitude in the Equinoctial; the ſecond Ship made in her ſecond Traverſe 23 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> to the difference of Longitude in the Equinoctial; the ſecond Ship made in her firſt Traverſe 70 <hi>d.</hi> 20 <hi>m.</hi>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:135346:72"/> and you have 93 <hi>d.</hi> 45 <hi>m.</hi> the difference of Longitude in the Equinoctial of the ſecond Ship from the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> in the Latitude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> Thus I have given you a full accompt of <hi>Mercator</hi>'s Practicai Rules in Navigation.</p>
               <p>Having given you a brief accompt of the Practical part of Navigation, according to the Common Chart, and according to the brief Rules of <hi>Merca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> I ſhall proceed to ſhew you how the Meridional parts, contained in the difference of Latitude, and the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of Longitude in the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial, and the difference of Latitude in each ſingle Traverſe, according to <hi>Mercator,</hi> is onely in proportion to the difference of Longitude, contained in each ſingle Traverſe in all right lined Triangles; Then I ſhall ſhew you that the like Rules of <hi>Mercator</hi> are out of all proportion with the difference of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude, in a right lined Triangle from the <hi>Lyzard</hi> according to his Practical Rules in Navigation, the Queſtions to be Reſolved by <hi>Mercator</hi>'s brief Rules are as follow in Example.</p>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:135346:72"/>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt Ship ſails from the <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard,</hi> Latitude 50 <hi>d.</hi> into the Latitude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> I find my difference of Latitude in Meridional parts 1417 the difference of Longitude in the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial is 4155 miles; the difference of Latitude is 1055 miles. I demand the difference of Longitude, in a right lined Triangle that the firſt Ship made according to the Common Chart from the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> A B.</p>
               <p>To find the difference of Longitude of the firſt Ship in a right lined Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angle, according to <hi>Mercator</hi>'s brief Rules, ſay as the Logarithm of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridional parts contained in the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of Latitude 1417, 315136, is to the Logarithm of the difference of Longitude in the Equinoctial 4155 miles, 361857. So is the Logarithm of the difference of Latitude 1055 miles, 302325, to the Logarithm of the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of Longitude, in a right lined Triangle, 349046, or 3093 miles, which is equal to the difference of Longitude, the firſt Ship made in a right lined Triangle. See the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:135346:73"/> Demonſtration, according to the Common Chart, A B.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond Ship ſails from the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> Latitude 50 <hi>d.</hi> into the Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of 65 <hi>d.</hi> 18 <hi>m.</hi> I find my diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Latitude in Meridional parts 1748. The difference of Longitude in the Equinoctial, is 4220 miles, the difference of Latitude is 918 miles, I demand the difference of Longitude, in a right lined Triangle, that the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Ship made according to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Chart, from the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> D C.</p>
               <p>To find the difference of Longitude of the ſecond Ship, in her firſt Traverſe, in a right lined Triangle, according to <hi>Mercator</hi>'s brief Rules, ſay as the Logarithm of the Meridional parts contained in the difference of Latitude, 1748, 324254; is to the Logarithm of the difference of Longitude in the Equinoctial; 4220 miles, 362531, ſo is the Logarithm of the difference of Latitude, 918 miles, 296284 to the Logarithm of the difference of Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, in a right lined Triangle 334561
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:135346:73"/> or 2217 miles, which is equal to the difference of Longitude, the ſecond made in a right lined Triangle in her firſt Traverſe. See the foregoing De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration, according to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Chart, D C.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The ſecond Ship ſails from C. in the Latitude of 65 <hi>d.</hi> 18 <hi>m.</hi> into the Latitude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> I find my difference of Latitude in the Meridio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal parts, 3165. The difference of Longitude, in the Equinoctial is 1405 miles, the difference of Latitude is 1973 miles; I demand the difference of Longitude, in a right lined Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angle; that the ſecond Ship made in her ſecond Traverſe, according to the Common Chart from E to B.</p>
               <p>To find the difference of Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, the ſecond Ship made in her ſecond Traverſe, in a right lined Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angle; ſay as the Logarithm of the Meridional parts, contained in the difference of Latitude 3165, 350037, is to the Logarithm of the difference of
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:135346:74"/> Longitude in the Equinoctial 1405 miles, 314767. So is the Logarithm of the difference of Latitude 1973 miles 329512 to the Logarithm of the difference of Longitude, in a right lined Triangle, 294242 or 876 miles which is equal to the difference of Longitude, the ſecond Ship made in a right lined Triangle, in her ſecond Traverſe: See the foregoing Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration according to the Common Chart; then add the difference of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude the ſecond Ship made in a right lined Triangle in her firſt Traverſe, 2217 miles found according to <hi>Merca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi>'s brief Rules to the difference of Longitude, the ſecond Ship made in a right lined Triangle in her ſecond Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe 876 miles, found according to <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator</hi>'s brief Rules; and you have 3093 miles equal to the difference of Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, the firſt Ship made in a right lined Triangle 3093: So that <hi>Mercator</hi>'s brief Rules are in proportion to the Rumb, and the difference of Latitude and the difference of Longitude in all ſingle Queſtions, in a right lined Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angle.
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:135346:74"/> See the forgoing Demonſtration which proves the Practical part of Navigation, performed by the ſecond Ship, according to the Common Chart, to be in the Meridian and Parallel of the firſt Ship.</p>
               <p>In the laſt place, I ſhall prove that the like Rules in the practical part of <hi>Mercator</hi>'s Navigation, will not give like difference of Longitude contained in the Traverſe of the ſecond Ship, in a right lined Triangle from the <hi>Lyzard</hi> 3093 miles, which will prove <hi>Merca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi>'s practical Poſition in Navigation to be notoriouſly falſe, for in the plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Rules of Art where propoſitions ſhall diſagree, we are to reject them. The Queſtion is as following.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>EXAMPLE.</label> According to <hi>Mercator</hi>'s Practical Rules in Navigation, the ſecond Ship in her ſecond Traverſe, is in the Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> the <hi>Lyzard</hi> in the Latitude of 50 <hi>d.</hi> The difference of Latitude in Meridional parts, 1417;
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:135346:75"/> the difference of Longitude in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinoctial, according to <hi>Mercator</hi>'s practical Rules in Navigation is 93 <hi>d.</hi> 45 <hi>m.</hi> or 5625 miles. The difference of Latitude is 1055 miles. I demand the difference of Longitude in a right lined Triangle, between the <hi>Lyzard</hi> and the Ship in her ſecond Traverſe.</p>
               <p>To find the difference of Longitude, in a right lined Triangle, ſay as the Logarithm of the Meridional parts, contained in the difference of Latitude 1417, 315136 is to the Logarithm of the difference of Longitude in the Equinoctial, 5625 miles 375012 So is the Logarithm of the difference of Latitude 1055 miles, 302325 to the Logarithm of the difference of Longitude in a right lined Triangle, 362201 or 4188 miles between the <hi>Lyzard</hi> and the Ship, in the Latitude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> demanded.</p>
               <p>Then ſubtract the difference of Londitude found by the like Rules of <hi>Mercator,</hi> in each Traverſe in a right lined Triangle 3093 miles from the <hi>Lyzard</hi> to the Ship, in the Latitude of
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:135346:75"/> 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> from the difference of Longitude, found by the like Rules of <hi>Mercator,</hi> in a right lined Triangle, according to <hi>Mercator</hi>'s practical Rules in Navigation 4188 miles, and you have 1095 miles or 18 <hi>d.</hi> 15 <hi>m.</hi> that <hi>Mercator</hi>'s practical Rules in Naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion doth differ from <hi>Mercator</hi>'s practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Rules in each Traverſe, in a right lined Triangle in the Latitude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> So that <hi>Mercator</hi> doth alter the Rumb and the diſtance and the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Longitude in the practical part of Navigation, from the <hi>Lyzard</hi> 1095 miles or 18 <hi>d.</hi> 15 <hi>m.</hi> more Weſt in the Latitude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Mercator</hi>'s Poſition in the practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal part of Navigation is notoriouſly falſe; for in the plaineſt Rules of Art where propoſitions ſhall diſagree we are to reject them.</p>
               <p>To ſumm up the foregoing Treatiſe, In the firſt place, I have proved the plain Chart, that has been rejected by all Writers, to be the onely true Chart in Navigation, by Obſervation and Demonſtration to which the Arithme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:135346:76"/> Rules are in proportion. Secondly, I have proved <hi>Mercator</hi>'s Arithmetical Rules, to be out of all proportion in the practical part of Navigation; and Geometry, In regard the whole Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants of <hi>Mercator</hi>'s Navigation, is upon his brief Rules in Arithmetick; which Rules diſagreeing, diſappoints the Deſign of Geometry: Therefore the work of Navigation cannot be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by <hi>Mercator:</hi> Thirdly, I have proved the Art of Navigation cannot be performed by the Arch of a great Circle; In regard the Arch of a great Circle doth meaſure the neareſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of places in North and South Latitude without having any regard to the Parallels of Latitude; ſo that the Angles of Poſition in the Arch of a great Circle doth differ from the Angles of Poſition, by the Magnetick Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs. See the foregoing Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: So that you cannot give the Queſtion as it ſtands in the practical part of Navigation to find the Meridian and Parallel the Ship is in by the Arch of a great Circle; neither can the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:135346:76"/> and Parallel of places be known upon the Globe, but as it is transferred to the Globe from the Common Chart, of which I ſhall give you a farther Account in the following Diſcourſe. The chief intent of this Treatiſe, is principally for Information, that all Men may give an Accompt of the Certainty of Navigation: Therefore I deſire Mr. <hi>Flamſteed,</hi> and the reſt of our Shore Navigators, to let the World ſee ſomething of their skill in Naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that they will not hide their Talent in a Napkin, but allow or diſprove what I have made publick to the World, which I expect from them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To transfer the Meridian and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel of places from the Common Chart, to the Globe.</head>
               <p>As the Meridian and Parallel of places, cannot be found by <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator</hi>'s practical Rules in Navigation, or by the Arch of a great Circle; ſo likewiſe you cannot transfer the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:135346:77"/> Meridian and Parallel of places from the Common Chart, to the Globe; but it muſt be transferred onely from one Meridian and Parallel of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Chart.</p>
               <p>Then by the following Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by which I transfer the Meridian and Parallel of places from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Chart to the Globe: You ſhall have the ſame Latitude and diſtance of places upon the Globe, as is upon the Common Chart, from that Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian and Parallel from whence it is transferred, otherwiſe the Meridian and Parallel of places cannot be known upon the Globe, as it is found by the practical Part of Navigation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To transfer the Meridian and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel of Places, from the Common Chart to the Globe.</head>
               <p n="1">
                  <label>EXAMPLE.</label> 1. In the Common Chart, the firſt Ship ſails from the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> L in the Latitude of 50 <hi>d.</hi> into the Latitude of
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:135346:77"/> 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> B, her diſtance ſailed is 3268 miles or 54 <hi>d.</hi> 28 <hi>m.</hi> L B, then take with your Compaſs 54 <hi>d.</hi> 28 <hi>m.</hi> L B, from the Equinoctial part of your Globe; placing one Foot of your Compaſs in the Latitude of 50<hi>d.</hi> of your Globe for the Meridian and Parallel of the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> then turn the Globe Eaſt, in regard your Ship is gone to the Weſt-ward, untill the other point doth cutt under the Braſs Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian of the Globe, in the Latitude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> there make a Mark which is the Meridian and Parallel of the firſt Ship upon the Globe. To prove the Truth of this Demonſtration, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the difference of Longitude be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Meridian of the <hi>Lyzard</hi> and the Meridian of your Mark, in the Equinoctial part of your Globe is 69 <hi>d.</hi> 15 <hi>m.</hi> as it was found by the brief Rules of <hi>Mercator.</hi> So that you have three certain diſtances upon the Globe, as is in a right lined Triangle; that is the difference of Latitude and the diſtance of places, and the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Longitude in the middle Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel.
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:135346:78"/> I ſhall proceed to the ſecond Ship.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To transfer the Meridian and Parallel of the ſecond Ship, in her firſt Traverſe, from the Meridian and Parallel of the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> according to the Common Chart, to the Globe. Example in the Common Chart, the ſecond Ship ſailed from the <hi>Lyzard</hi> L in the Latitude of 50 <hi>d.</hi> into the Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of 65 <hi>d.</hi> 18 <hi>m.</hi> C her diſtance ſails is 2400 miles or 40 <hi>d.</hi> L C, then take with your Compaſs 40 <hi>d.</hi> from the Equinoctial part of your Globe, placing one Foot in the Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of 50 <hi>d.</hi> as you did before for the Meridian and Parallel of the <hi>Lyzard:</hi> Then turn the Globe Eaſt-ward, in regard your Ship is gone to the Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, untill the other point doth cutt under the Braſs Meridian, in the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of 65 <hi>d.</hi> 18 <hi>m.</hi> there make a Mark which is the Meridian and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel of the ſecond Ship in her firſt Traverſe, from the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> upon the Globe. To prove the Truth of this
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:135346:78"/> Demonſtration, obſerve the difference of Longitude between the Meridian of the <hi>Lyzard</hi> and the Meridian of your mark in the Equinoctial part of your Globe is 70 <hi>d.</hi> 20 <hi>m.</hi> as it was found by the brief Rules of <hi>Mercator;</hi> ſo that you have Three certain diſtances upon the Globe, as is in a right lined Triangle, that is the difference of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude and the diſtance of places, and the difference of Longitude in the middle Parallel. I ſhall proceed to the ſecond Ship in her ſecond Traverſe.</p>
               <p>To transfer the Meridian and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel of the ſecond Ship, in her ſecond Traverſe, from the Meridian and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel of the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> according to the Common Chart, to the Globe, Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the ſecond Ship in her ſecond Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, ſails from C in the Latitude of 65 <hi>d.</hi> 18 <hi>m.</hi> in an Angle of 23 <hi>d.</hi> 56 <hi>m.</hi> South-weſt-ward. 2159 miles to B and meets the firſt Ship, in the Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> at B. ſo that the diſtance of the ſecond Ship from the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> B L is 3268 miles, and is equal to the diſtance of the firſt Ship
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:135346:79"/> from the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> B L, 3268. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Latitude of the <hi>Lyzard</hi> 50 <hi>d.</hi> L and the Latitude of the ſecond Ship in her ſecond Traverſe 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> B and the diſtance of the ſecond Ship in her ſecond Traverſe from the <hi>Lyzard</hi> 3268 miles B L or 54 <hi>d.</hi> 28 <hi>m.</hi> is in the like proportion to the Meridian and Parallel of the firſt Ship in the Common Chart, as it is transferred to the Globe, from the Common Chart, and is in the like proportion to the difference of Longitude in the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial of the firſt Ship from the <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard</hi> 69 <hi>d.</hi> 15 <hi>m.</hi> This Demonſtration muſt be Infallibly True, in regard <hi>Mercator</hi>'s brief Rules, and the Rules of the Globe are in proportion to the difference of Longitude in all right lined Triangles; as in the foregoing Triangle between A and B.</p>
               <p>In the laſt place, I ſhall prove the Meridian and Parallel of all the known parts of the World, muſt be onely transferred from one Meridian and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel of the Common Chart to the Globe, otherwiſe you will alter the
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:135346:79"/> Meridian and Parallel of places upon the Globe, as they are transferred from onely one Meridian and Parallel of the Common Chart: In regard the Meridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal parts contained in the difference of Latitude, and the Rumb, according to <hi>Mercator,</hi> are onely in proportion to the difference of Longitude in the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial, in a ſingle Traverſe, but not in the practical part of Navigation, by which the Meridian and Parallel of all the known parts of the World is found.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>EXAMPLE.</label> The ſecond Ship, in her ſecond Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, ſails from C in the Latitude of 65 <hi>d.</hi> 18 <hi>m.</hi> in an Angle of 23 <hi>d.</hi> 56 <hi>m.</hi> 2159 miles or 35 <hi>d.</hi> 59 <hi>m.</hi> into the Latitude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> Then take with your Compaſs 35 <hi>d.</hi> 59 <hi>m.</hi> the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance ſailed from the Equinoctial part of the Globe, placing one Foot in the Meridian and Parallel of the ſecond Ship, in her firſt Traverſe, as it was transferred from the Common Chart
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:135346:80"/> the Globe; then turn the Globe Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, in regard your Ship is gone to the Weſt-ward untill the other Point doth cutt under the Braſs Meridian of the Globe, in the Latitude of 32 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> there make a mark upon the Globe, and you ſhall have 23 <hi>d.</hi> 25 <hi>m.</hi> the difference of Longitude in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinoctial, as it was found by <hi>Merca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi>'s brief Rules in that ſingle Traverſe, which being added to the difference of Longitude in the Equinoctial, that the ſecond Ship made in her firſt Traverſe from the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> 70 <hi>d.</hi> 20 <hi>m.</hi> You have 93 <hi>d.</hi> 45 <hi>m.</hi> the difference of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude in the Equinoctial, Weſt of the Meridian of the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> then ſubtract 69 <hi>d.</hi> 15 <hi>m.</hi> the difference of Longitude in the Equinoctial, the ſecond Ship made in proportion to the difference of Longitude in each ſingle Traverſe in a right lined Triangle, from the <hi>Lyzard,</hi> according to the practical Rules of <hi>Mercator</hi> in each Traverſe, and you have 24 <hi>d.</hi> 30 <hi>m.</hi> that you muſt alter the Meridian and Parallel of the ſecond Ship in the Equinoctial
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:135346:80"/> part of the Globe, which proves <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator</hi>'s practical Rules in Navigation to be notoriouſly falſe. In regard <hi>Merca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi>'s Rules doth diſagree in the practical Part, with the Rumb and the right lines of the Magnetick Compaſs. Therefore as the Meridian and Parallel of places cannot be found by the practical part of Navigation by the Arch of a great Circle, or by the brief Rules of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator;</hi> ſo likewiſe you cannot transfer the Meridian and Parallel of places from the Common Chart to the Globe, but onely from one Meridian and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel of the Common Chart, by ſuch Demonſtrations you ſhall have the ſame Latitudes and diſtance of places to all the known parts of the World, upon the Globe, as it is transferred from any one Meridian and Parallel of the Common Chart, otherwiſe the Meridian and Parallel of places cannot be known upon the Globe, as they are found by the practical part of Naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; therefore the Common Chart, is the onely True Chart in Navigation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:135346:81"/>
               <head>In the laſt place.</head>
               <p>There have been ſome that pretend to find the difference of Longitude or the difference of Meridians, by Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation from the Celeſtial Bodies; firſt I ſhall prove it is not to be found by ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation from the Stars: Secondly, I ſhall prove it is not to be found by ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation from the Planets, upon their greateſt inclination or declination into the Equinoctial, without it be when the Sun or Moon be Eclipſed in the Equinoctial.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In the firſt place, I ſhall prove the difference of Meridians, or the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Longitude cannot be found by obſervation from the Stars.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>EXAMPLE.</label> Suppoſe your ſelf to be in any Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian and Parallel of the Terreſtial Sphere, there you take the Meridian altitude, of one or more Stars in the
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:135346:81"/> Equinoctial, or out of the Equinoctial, the Meridian altitude of thoſe Stars: or the altitude of the guards upon their Angles of Poſition with the North Star is the ſame the whole Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation of the Earth, in that Parallel you made your Obſervations in, ſo that you have no difference of Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to give the difference of Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, or the difference of Meridians. Therefore the difference of Longitude, or the difference of Meridians cannot be found by Obſervation, from any of the Stars, without you have difference of Obſervation, to give the difference of Meridians.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In the next place, I ſhall prove the difference of Longitude or the difference of Meridians cannot be found by Obſervation, from any of the Planets upon their greateſt inclination or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination into the Equinoctial, or day after day.</p>
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:135346:82"/>
               <p>
                  <label>EXAMPLE.</label> If you obſerve in any Meridian and Parallel of the World, the Meridian altitude of any of the Planets, upon their greateſt inclination or declination into the Equinoctial, or day after day, you will find the difference in your Obſervations, in any one Meridian and Parallel you obſerve in, not to have a proportion to the difference of Longitude or the difference of Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians with the circulation of the Earth, therefore the difference of Longitude or the difference of Meridians cannot be found by Obſervation from the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian altitude of any of the Planets without you have difference of obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. In proportion to the difference of Longitude or the difference of Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians the circulation of the Earth.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In the laſt place, I ſhall ſhew you how the difference of Longitude or the difference of Meridians may be found by Obſervation when Eclipſes
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:135346:82"/> ſhall happen to be in the Equinoctial and not otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>EXAMPLE.</label> If the Sun or Moon be Eclipſed in the Equinoctial, and that ſeveral per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in ſeveral Meridians and Parallels of the World, doth obſerve the alti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the Sun or Moon, at the beginning or end of the Eclipſe, theſe Obſervations being compared, the difference of Obſervation between ſuch places, ſhall give the difference Longitude or the difference of Meridians between thoſe places ſuch Obſervations were made in, In regard the Sun or Moon being E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſed in the Equinoctial doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear at that inſtant of time thoſe Obſervations were taken at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning or end of the Eclipſe as a Pole in the Eaſt or Weſt, ſo that the difference of Longitude or the difference of Meridians muſt have
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:135346:83"/> the like proportions by Obſervation from ſuch Eclipſes, to prove the Meridians doth run Parallel to the Eaſt and Weſt part of the Terreſtial Sphere, as the Parallels of Latitude are proved to run Parallel by Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation to the the Equinoctial and to the North and South Pole of the Terreſtial Sphere, therefore it is a very ſtrange Opinion in any Men to grant the Magnetick Compaſs rectified to his true Poles to run Eaſt or Weſt in all Parallels of Latitude to the Equinoctial, and to the Poles of North and South, and not to grant the Meridians of the Magnetick Compaſs to run Parallel to the Eaſt and Weſt part of the Terreſtial Sphere; in the foregoing Treatiſe, I have proved by Obſervation, that the Magnetick Compaſs in all Meridians and Parallels of the World doth point to the Eaſt and Weſt part of the Celeſtial Sphere, as it points to the North and South part of the Celeſtial Sphere; therefore
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:135346:83"/> as the Magnetick Compaſs makes the ſame Poſition to the Eaſt and Weſt part of the Celeſtial Sphere as it doth to the North and South part of the Celeſtial Sphere, in all Meridians and Parallels of the World: therefore it muſt be granted that the Magnetick Compaſs runs in Parallel Meridians, as it runs in Parallels of Latitude up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on the Terreſtial Sphere; to which the Obſervations of Eclipſes in the Equinoctial, and the Obſervations from the Poles of the North and South doth agree.</p>
               <p n="4">4. In the laſt place, If the Sun or Moon be not Eclipſed in the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial, then the altitude of the Sun or Moon being obſerved in ſeveral Meridians and Parallels at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning or end of the Eclipſe, the difference of ſuch Obſervations being compared cannot give the difference of Meridians or the difference of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude in proportion with the Parallels of Latitude; In regard the Sun or
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:135346:84"/> Moon ſo Eclipſed out of the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial, ſuch Obſervations cannot croſs the Parallels of Latitude at right Angles: For ſuch Obſervations are as much out of proportion with the Parallels of Latitude, as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel Meridians of the Poles Ecliptick, would be out of proportion with the Parallel Meridians, of the North and South Poles, upon the Terreſtial Sphere. So that the difference of Longitude or the difference of Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians upon the Terreſtial Sphere, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be found by Obſervation from the Stars, or from the Planets, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it be when the Sun and Moon be Eclipſed in the Equinoctial.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="147" facs="tcp:135346:84"/>
            <head>To Prove the Earth the Centre of the <hi>Starry-Heaven,</hi> and not to have any Inclination towards the Poles, as <hi>Coper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicus</hi> would have it.</head>
            <p>THE Earth by Obſervation keeps its Parallels with the Starry-Heaven all the Year, without altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for by Obſervation, that Star that is in the Equinoctial part of Heaven, is always in the Equinoctial part of the Earth; ſo likewiſe, take all the Stars in their ſeveral Parallels to the Poles from the Equinoctial, and you will find they keep their Parallels with the Earth for ever.</p>
            <p>We need not go to the Equinoctial part of the Earth, to prove the Earth
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:135346:85"/> to keep her Parallels with the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial part of the Starry Heaven: For, obſerve in this Parallel or Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of <hi>London</hi> 51 <hi>d.</hi> 30 <hi>m.</hi> the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plitude of any Star in the Equinoctial, either upon his Riſing or Setting, and you ſhall find Amplitude to be Eaſt or Weſt of you for ever, in this Parallel or any other.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe obſerve the Meridian Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of any Star in the Equinoctial, in this Parallel or in any other Parallel or Latitudes, and you ſhall find his Meridian Altitude to be the Elevation of the Equinoctial for ever, in this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel, or Latitude, or in any other Parallel or Latitudes.</p>
            <p>And by daily Obſervations we find the Sun to alter his Amplitudes, and Meridian Altitudes, and Parallels with the Starry Heaven and the Earth. And we find the Starry Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to keep its Parallels with the Earth always, in regard the Stars keep their Meridian Altitudes and Amplitudes with the Earth, without alteration.</p>
            <pb n="149" facs="tcp:135346:85"/>
            <p>But if we ſhould admit the Sun the Centre of the Starry Heaven, and the Earth ſhould have her Declination towards her Poles; then the Sun muſt be always in the Equinoctial part of the Starry Heaven; and the Sun muſt have the ſame Amplitudes, and Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian Altitudes, with the Stars in the Equinoctial, in all Parallels! And then the Sun, and all the Stars in Heaven, ſhould have a daily Calculation of the Declination of the Earth, as the Earth ſhould alter her Parallels, by Inclining or Declining towards her Poles.</p>
            <p>But it is proved by Obſervation, that the Sun cannot be the Centre of the Starry-Heaven; in regard the Sun is not always in the Equinoctial part of that Heaven, and the Sun hath not the ſame Meridian Altitude, and Ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and Parallels, with the Starry-Heaven in the Equinoctial, but twice in the Year, and that is as the Sun Inclines and Declines from one Tropick to another.</p>
            <pb n="150" facs="tcp:135346:86"/>
            <p>And it is proved by Obſervation, that the Equinoctial part of the Star<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry-Heaven is always in the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial part of the Earth, for the Meridian Altitude of the Stars in Equinoctial is the Elevation of the Equinoctial in all Parallels. Now there is a neceſſity, that the Declina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sun ſhould be Calculated for every day in the Year, in regard of his Declination towards his Poles 23 <hi>d.</hi> 30 <hi>m.</hi> which is the cauſe the Sun alters his Parallels, and Ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, and Meridian Altitudes every day.</p>
            <p>But for Stars in the Starry-Heaven, their Declination or diſtance from the Equinoctial is the ſame for ever, and keeps its Parallels with the Earth, by Obſervation.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:135346:86"/>
               <head>Another Example from the Sun, to prove the Earth the Centre of the <hi>Starry-Heaven.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MOST <hi>Mathematicians</hi> hold, that when the Sun is depreſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Horizon 15 <hi>d.</hi> that Twylight appears upon the Horizon; the proof of which is very ſutable in this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel or Latitude.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>EXAMPLE.</label> 
                  <hi>London,</hi> Latitude 51 <hi>d.</hi> 30. North, the Suns Declination 23 <hi>d.</hi> 30 <hi>m.</hi> North, the Suns Depreſſion 15 <hi>d.</hi> 00 <hi>m.</hi> I demand the Time of Twylight? By the Work you will find the Sun be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:135346:87"/> depreſſed 15 <hi>d.</hi> at Midnight, the 11th day of <hi>June,</hi> in the Latitude of 51 <hi>d.</hi> 30. you will have Twylight appear in the North all Night: At which time we find by Obſervation in the Equinoctial, and in this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel, and in all other Parallels, the Sun to be diſtant from the North Poles 66 <hi>d.</hi> 30 <hi>m.</hi> Now if the Sun was the Centre of the Starry-Heaven, the Sun would be always diſtant from the Poles 90 <hi>d.</hi> as the Stars in the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial are, and as the Sun is the 10th day of <hi>March,</hi> or the 10th day of <hi>September,</hi> when he is in the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial.</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>I ſhall add one Obſervation more from the Magnetick Compaſs, as it is Horizontal to prove the Earth the Centre of the Starry-Heaven.</head>
                  <p>It is granted by all Aſtronomers, that Stars of the leaſt Magnitude, are bigger than the Earth, ſo that the
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:135346:87"/> leaſt Star appears as a Centre to us upon the Earth; In like manner I ſhall prove the Earth by Obſervation by the Magnetick Compaſs, appears but as a Centre to the Stars, and that the Earth is the Centre of the Starry-Heaven.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>EXAMPLE.</label> The Magnetick Compaſs as it is Horizontal in all Meridians and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallels of the World rectified to its true Poles, where there is occaſion, doth point to the Stars in the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial, and to the Eaſt and Weſt, and to the North and South parts of the Celeſtial Sphere, croſſing the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial Sphere at right Angles, without giving any difference of Obſervation for the Diameter of the Earth, ſo that the Earth appears as a Centre to the Stars and is the Centre of the Starry Heaven, by the Horizontal Obſervations of the Magnetick Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs; in regard you have no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:135346:88"/> of Obſervation, for the whole Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ameter of the Earth; but if the Earth ſhould incline or decline towards its Poles as <hi>Copernicus</hi> ſuppoſed it doth, 23 <hi>d.</hi> 30 <hi>m.</hi> then the Horizontal Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Magnetick Compaſs can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not point to the Stars in the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial, or to the Eaſt and Weſt part of the Celeſtial Sphere, for if the Earth, as a Centre ſhould move upon its Axis 23 <hi>d.</hi> 30 <hi>m.</hi> to each Tropick, then the Earth muſt alter the Equinoctial part of the Starry Heaven, as the Sun and the reſt of the Planets doth, therefore <hi>Copernicus</hi> is under a very great mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, to ſuppoſe the Sun the Centre of the Starry Heaven.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>In the next place, I ſhall prove the foregoing poſition by Obſervation and by Demonſtration, the outward, Sphere repreſenting the Starry-hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the leſſer Sphere the Earth.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. To demonſtrate the Earth to be the Centre of the Starry Heaven. If
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:135346:88"/> the Earth ſhould move upon its Axis 23 <hi>d.</hi> 30 <hi>m.</hi> towards the North or South Poles, then there is a neceſſity the Earth muſt alter its Parallels with the Sun and the Stars in the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial part of Heaven, 23 <hi>d.</hi> 30 <hi>m.</hi> but on the contrary it is proved by Obſervation in all Meridians and Parallels of the World, that A is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in the Equinoctial part of the Starry-Heaven, and that B is always in the Tropick of <hi>Cancer;</hi> and that C is always in the Tropick of <hi>Capri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corn,</hi> ſo that the Earth always keeps its Parallels with the Starry-Heaven without alteration; therefore the Earth is the Centre of the Starry-Heaven.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If the Sun ſhould be the Centre of the Starry-Heaven, according to <hi>Copernicus</hi>'s ſuppoſition; then the Sun by Obſervation ſhould be always in the Equinoctial part of the Starry-Heaven, as it is the tenth day of <hi>March,</hi> and the tenth day of <hi>September,</hi> at which time the Sun is by Obſervation diſtant
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:135346:89"/> from the Poles, 90 <hi>m.</hi> but on the contrary the Sun is by Obſervation when he is in the Tropicks 66 <hi>d.</hi> 30 <hi>m.</hi> diſtant from the Poles; therefore the Sun doth alter its place in the Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick with the Conſtellations of the Starry-Heaven, by inclining from the Tropick of <hi>Capricorn,</hi> to the Tropick of <hi>Cancer</hi> 47 <hi>d.</hi> ſo that the Sun can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be the Centre of the Starry-Heaven but by ſuppoſition.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>geometrical diagram</figDesc>
                     <head>between pag. 156 and 157.</head>
                  </figure>
                  <p>What I have offered to the World in this ſmall Treatiſe, I have proved by Obſervation and Demonſtration; therefore whatever Men may pretend to, if they do not accord with the like Rules, it is but Fancy or Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
